<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/BarnstableMAWest-5285.xml"
      >BarnstableMAWest-5285</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/BarnstableMAWest-5285.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Barnstable, Mass. West Parish Church records, 1639-1853. </titleproper>
        <author>Sari Mauro, Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-04-01</date>
        <num>RG5285</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>Portions of this collection are part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital
          historical representations of these portions of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-04-01T19:57:02+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Monday April 1, 2019
          at 19:57</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Barnstable, Mass. West Parish Church records, 1639-1853.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5285</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>0.22</quantity>
        <unittype>Cubic Feet</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(1 box)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1639">1639</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1853">1853</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1639-1853</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_e23e0aa4815b1fd0380d7019f59bf09d">The history of the West Parish Church
        in Barnstable, Massachusetts, dates back to 1616 with the formation of the non-conformist
        Southwick Church. In 1634 the leader of the church and many of its members traveled to
        Boston and in 1639 settled in the newly incorporated Barnstable where they formed the first
        church in Barnstable. In 1717 the town of Barnstable was split into a West and East Parish;
        the West Parish Church was the successor church to the earlier Barnstable church.
        Construction of the West Parish meeting house was started in 1717 and completed in 1719. It
        was renovated in 1852. It was completely restored to its original form between 1953 and
        1958. The West Parish Church continues to serve the local community today. This collection
        contains the earliest record book of the West Parish Church and some supplementary
        materials. These records include meeting minutes, ecclesiastical council results, vital
        records, and records of church discipline and controversies.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="no96004569" source="lcnaf">
          <part>West Parish Church (West Barnstable, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_8fb49f80820e8b05a56c4aaf352271d7">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_9739d6f6531cb4772470bcf0edee64c2">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_d2822a4bbfbc1e55870214a6fba13575">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Barnstable, Mass. West Parish Church records, 1639-1853,
        RG5285. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_72f1d23ad2197b6215944e49af086412">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Materials were loaned to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives by the West Parish
        Church in Barnstable, Massachusetts, in June 2015; 2015-08.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <custodhist id="aspace_d15361d47c9c84e8bbfa80896bbc5d8b">
      <head>Custodial History</head>
      <p>Materials were loaned to the Massachusetts Historical Society before they were loaned to
        the Congregational Library &amp; Archives.</p>
      <p>The Church record book underwent extensive preservation work prior to its arrival at the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives. Neither the date nor the vendor for this preservation
        work is known.</p>
    </custodhist>
    <processinfo id="aspace_b1ef838981ec671d80644578ecd12c78">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Sari Mauro, July 2015, using DACS Second Edition. Reprocessed and redescribed
        by Zachary Bodnar, April 2019, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_2f087a9c1bb3fa11f6f919a48c3bd028">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The history of the West Parish Congregational church begins with the gathering of a small
        non-conformist church in Southwark, London, 1616. At the gathering of that church Henry
        Jacob was appointed as pastor. Henry Jacob resigned from the church in 1622 in order to
        travel to Jamestown, Virginia, where he died in 1624. Henry Jacob's successor was Rev. John
        Lothrop, a young Oxford graduate and strong proponent of the separation of church and state.
        In 1632, while gathered for worship in a private home, Lothrop and the members of the church
        present, were arrested for their non-conformist beliefs. During their imprisonment, Rev.
        Lothrop's wife died from medical complications. In the summer of 1634, Lothrop was released
        from prison on the condition of his banishment; by September of 1634 Lothrop and
        approximately 30 members of the Southwark Church arrived in Boston.</p>
      <p>The members of the Southwark church initially settled in Scituate, a small settlement in
        the Plymouth Colony. Discord between the members of the Southwark Church and the other
        Plymouth Colony settlers quickly developed over the distribution of land and the issue of
        baptism. Lothrop petitioned the General Court for resettlement and in June of 1638 the Court
        offered Lothrop and his church land in the recently settled Mattakeese, now Barnstable. They
        arrived in October of 1639, a month after the town of Barnstable was officially
        incorporated.</p>
      <p>Barnstable had initially been settled by another puritan minister, Rev. Joseph Hull. The
        early settlement could not support two congregations and the Southwark Church outnumbered
        Hull's. Further, some of the members of Hull's congregation switched and joined the
        Southwark Church. The result was that shortly after Lothrop's settlement in Barnstable, Hull
        moved to Yarmouth and left the religious administration of the new settlement to Lothrop.
        This marked the official gathering of the Parish Church in Barnstable. Within three years of
        their settlement construction on the first meeting house began; construction was completed
        in 1644. This building continues to stand today and is a part of the Sturgis Library in
        Barnstable.</p>
      <p>Rev. Lothrop died in 1653. Discord within the church lasted until 1663 when Thomas Walley
        was settled as the second minister. He served as pastor until 1673 when he died. Another ten
        year period of discord followed until the settlement of Johnathan Russell in 1683. He was
        succeeded by his son, Johnathan Russell II in 1712. By 1712 Barnstable had grown
        significantly and some members of the parish began to push for a division of Barnstable into
        an East and West Parish. Johnathan Russell II attempted to thwart this decision but in 1715
        the town voted for the division and an Ecclesiastical Council made permanent the town vote.
        The Parish Church in Barnstable became the West Parish Church in 1717 while the East Parish
        Church officially was gathered as a new church in 1723. Construction on the second meeting
        house began in 1717 and was completed in 1719.</p>
      <p>The meeting house was enlarged in 1723. During the enlargement, a new bell tower was added
        to the building as well as a gilded cock weathervane that had been ordered from England. In
        the early 1760s, the newly installed minister, Rev. Oakes Shaw purchased a home which later
        became the parsonage. By 1852 the meeting house had fallen into disrepair. However, the
        church was poor, largely due to the decreased prosperity of Barnstable and the greater
        number of churches present in the town, so instead of building a new meeting house, the
        church voted to completely renovate the meeting house. During the ministry of Rev. Henry A.
        Goodhue (1863-1883), Goodhue maintained a small school in the vestry of the meeting
        house.</p>
      <p>The economic situation of the church continued to deteriorate into the twentieth-century.
        In 1920 the church voted to work with the South Congregational Church in Centerville to
        share a single minister between the two churches. Both churches were struggling financially
        and had been constant beneficiaries of home mission aid. This relationship stood unchanged
        until 1957. By 1950 the church building had once again falling into significant disrepair.
        Largely due to the efforts of Elizabeth Jenkins, a member of the church, the West Parish
        Memorial Foundation was incorporated in 1950 with the mission of raising $100,000 to fully
        restore the church to its 1719 form. In 1953 work on the restoration began and continued
        until 1958 with the installation of an organ. During the 1950s the church joined the United
        Church of Christ. In 1962 the West Parish Church merged with the West Barnstable Finnish
        Congregational Church.</p>
      <p>The West Parish Church, UCC, in Barnstable continues to serve the local community today.
        The church continues to meet in the 1719 meeting house making it the oldest in-use meeting
        house in the world.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_a4b88aa3f9edd4618a7106d45959f004">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains the earliest record book of the West Parish Church in Barnstable
        and materials supplementary to that record book. The collection includes administrative
        meeting minutes, results of ecclesiastical councils, records of disciplinary cases, vital
        membership records, baptismal records, marriage intentions and documents related to a
        controversy over music and singing during church services.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_1bb9195b395368020fa330ee3c9dafdb">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Materials have been arranged in chronological order by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_17a881b2a187df4780027432c5191e26">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_28bccb95aa85f5366acc73aa68e352af">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>The early history of the West Parish Church in Barnstable is intrinsically linked to the
        history of the East Parish Church in Barnstable which is now the Unitarian Church in
        Barnstable. Digital representations of the earliest records of the East Parish Church are
        available through the Congregational Library &amp; Archives <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/nehh/series1/BarnstableMAWest5285"
          linktitle="View the East Parish Church of Barnstable records online" show="new">to view
          online</ref>. The physical records of the East Parish Church, and the Unitarian Church it
        became, are available through the <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.sturgislibrary.org" linktitle="Visit the Sturgis Library website"
          show="new">Sturgis Library</ref> in Barnstable.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_115d7af47b85947d84a3bb720c1ddda0">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Goehring, Walter R. <emph render="italic">The West Parish Church of Barnstable: An
          Historical Sketch</emph>. The West Parish Memorial Foundation: West Barnstable, 1959.
        17.11.1 W52.2 WesPC</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025590" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church controversies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025597" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church discipline.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025649" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church membership.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85066724" source="lcsh">
        <part>Installation (clergy).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85081512" source="lcsh">
        <part>Marriage records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="n79103943" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Barnstable (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n91002162" source="lcnaf">
        <part>West Barnstable (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="no96004569" source="lcnaf">
        <part>West Parish Church (West Barnstable, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_54a57d08c22b39e79aa1c38eb92e0f57" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church record book</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1639">1639</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1853">1853</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1639-1853</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_87675089f560a37dbedc8363df5dd681" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_2e7121017b7bfb832dfab727a651913d" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_87675089f560a37dbedc8363df5dd681">1</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_38be32d31138a625ca9d6707cf620635">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/BarnstableWest/viewer/Church20records2C2016681807/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.
            Transcriptions for this volume are also available and may be viewed alongside the
            digital images.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_8d304f91335f2e2fa4452c05858aaac1">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the earliest administrative, ecclesiastical, and vital membership
            records of the West Parish Church. Included within the records are meeting minutes,
            ecclesiastical council reports, disciplinary records including written confessions,
            baptismal records, and records of admissions and dismissions. The volume also includes
            records related to a controversy over music and singing during church services.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_d508d31ff4b01072c86f3dac9c5aa836" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1835">1835</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1853">1853</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">circa 1835-1853</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_a7a5db356f6ed7a394f5ab9200c3a369" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_4f9aea69cee4b71ccbecd1aeb14567f4" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_a7a5db356f6ed7a394f5ab9200c3a369">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_c46662ee72e7939b4fd5be9bfc92635e">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This folder contains assorted records related to the operation of the West Parish
            Church. Included within the records are an index of the Church record book, sermon
            notes, marriage intentions, baptismal records, and the minutes of a pulpit supply
            meeting.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
