<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<collection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim" xmlns:marc="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim http://www.loc.gov/standards/marcxml/schema/MARC21slim.xsd">
  <record>
    <leader>00000npcaa2200000 u 4500</leader>
    <controlfield tag="008">240304i18912016xxu                 eng d</controlfield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="040">
      <subfield code="a">MBC</subfield>
      <subfield code="b">eng</subfield>
      <subfield code="c">MBC</subfield>
      <subfield code="e">DACS 2019.0.3</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="041">
      <subfield code="a">eng</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="049">
      <subfield code="a">MBC</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="099">
      <subfield code="a">RG5473</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2=" " tag="110">
      <subfield code="a">North Congregational Church,.</subfield>
      <subfield code="e">creator.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="1" ind2="0" tag="245">
      <subfield code="a">Berkeley, CA. Grace North Church records, 1891-2016.,</subfield>
      <subfield code="f">1891-2016</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="300">
      <subfield code="a">5.31</subfield>
      <subfield code="f">Cubic Feet ((7 boxes))</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="351">
      <subfield code="a">This collection has been arranged into five series from the Grace North Church. The Church Reports and Meeting Minutes series and the Auxiliary Organizations series have been further divdied into subseries. All of the series and subseries have been arranged into chronological order.  Series 1:  Vital Statistics, 1891-2016  Series 2:  Church Reports and Meeting Minutes, 1892-2010  Sub-series 1:  Meeting Minutes, 1892-2010  Sub-series 2:  Reports, 1914-2005  Series 3:  Auxiliary Organizations, 1899-1955, 1989-1996  Sub-series 1:  Ladies' Aid Society, 1899-1924  Sub-series 2:  Bay Association, 1921-1955  Sub-series 3:  Grace Institute of Religious Learning, 1989-1996  Series 4:  Finances, 1937-1973  Series 5:  Histories and Publications, 1942-1959, 1990-1998  Series 6:  Building and Architecture, 1948-1966, 1995-2010.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="500">
      <subfield code="a">Processing Information: Collection was processed in January 2024 by Billy McCarthy using DACS Second Edition.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="506">
      <subfield code="a">Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="3" ind2=" " tag="520">
      <subfield code="a">The North Grace Church’s origins began at a meeting on June 28, 1892 with twenty-four “charter members.” The newly formed church, then called the Congregational Church of North Berkeley, was led by Rev. David F. Taylor. The church closed as North Congregational Church in 1992. The church returned in 1995 as Grace North Church and remained open until 2023. This collection contains various records from across Grace North Church and includes topics like vital statistics, church reports and meeting minutes, auxiliary organizations, finances, histories and publications, and church buildings.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2=" " tag="520">
      <subfield code="a">This collection contains various records from across Grace North Church and includes topics like vital statistics, church reports and meeting minutes, auxiliary organizations, finances, histories and publications, and church buildings.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="524">
      <subfield code="a">[Identification of item], in the Berkeley, CA. Grace North Church records, 1891-2016, RG5473. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="540">
      <subfield code="a">Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="1" ind2=" " tag="541">
      <subfield code="a">Materials were donated to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives by Ric Reed, secretary of North Grace Church in August 2023; 2023-38.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="545">
      <subfield code="a">The North Grace Church’s origins began at a meeting on June 28, 1892, moderated by Rev. J.K. McLean and Rev. E.F. Dinsmore as the scribe. At this meeting, articles of faith and a covenant were accepted by twenty-six members. Two people would drop shortly after, leaving the new church with twenty-four “charter members.”  The newly formed church, then called the Congregational Church of North Berkeley, was led by Rev. David F. Taylor. A new church building was dedicated on May 21, 1893, at the southwest corner of Cedar and Oxford Streets. 

The Church was officially incorporated in California on September 25, 1895. The church’s membership was around 147 members in 1904, twelve years after being formed. The following year, the church building was moved to the rear of the lot and elevated to house Sunday School rooms, pastor’s study, and parlor. Out of this Sunday School grew the Chinese branch of North Church which would go on to become Berkeley Chinese Church in 1914. 

The now-called North Church steadily moved through the Depression and into the 1940s. On September 7, 1944, the church building was destroyed in a fire. The congregation met at various other locations for a couple of years until a new building was completed on January 16, 1949. Much of the process was led by Rev. Eugene Haynes alongside numerous other members of the community. 

In 1960, the North Congregational Church decided to join the United Church of Christ. This membership would last until 1968, when the church joined the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches. The church progressed through the 1970s, closing their Sunday School in 1975 due to low attendance. The church's overall membership declined through the 1980s, though benevolent giving continued to be strong. Continued decline in membership led to the church agreeing to close its doors in 1992, giving the land over to the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches. 

The closure in 1992 was not the end of the story and in 1995 fourteen former members of the North Congregational Church asked the Grace Institute to join and form a new church which would eventually be called Grace North Church. The Institute was filled with former members of the North Congregational Church and worshipped in the same building. Thus, the legacy of North Congregational Church was taken on by the Grace North Church. They rejoined the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches in June of 1995. This Grace North Church continued to serve the community until it officially closed in 2023.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2="4" tag="610">
      <subfield code="a">Grace North Church,.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2="7" tag="610">
      <subfield code="a">Congregational Church of North Berkeley,.</subfield>
      <subfield code="2">local</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2="7" tag="610">
      <subfield code="a">North Congregational Church,.</subfield>
      <subfield code="2">local</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2="0" tag="610">
      <subfield code="a">Berkeley (Calif.)</subfield>
      <subfield code="x">Church history.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Guest books.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh2001006720</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Women</subfield>
      <subfield code="x">Societies and clubs.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh85147343</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Church records and registers.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh85025741</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Church finance.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh85025606</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Church history.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh85025619</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Church membership.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh85025649</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Church buildings.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh85025854</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Christian education.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh85025042</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2="0" tag="650">
      <subfield code="a">Baptismal records.</subfield>
      <subfield code="0">sh89002058</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2=" " tag="710">
      <subfield code="a">Congregational Church of North Berkeley,.</subfield>
      <subfield code="e">creator.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1="2" ind2=" " tag="710">
      <subfield code="a">Grace North Church,.</subfield>
      <subfield code="e">creator.</subfield>
    </datafield>
    <datafield ind1=" " ind2=" " tag="852">
      <subfield code="a">MBC</subfield>
    </datafield>
  </record>
</collection>

