<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/BraintreeMAFirst-5302.xml"
      >BraintreeMAFirst-5302</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/finding-aids/BraintreeMAFirst5302"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Braintree, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1697-1871.</titleproper>
        <author>Jules Thomson, Corinne Bernstein</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2016-02-24</date>
        <num>RG5302</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition (DACS)</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2020-01-07T21:28:59+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday January 7,
          2020 at 21:28</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Braintree, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1697-1871.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5302</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>.44</quantity>
        <unittype>Cubic Feet</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(1 box)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1697">1697</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1871">1871</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1697-1871</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_fb25cb723912c6a92c0f0cfdf3af1402">The Mount Wollaston Parish Meeting
        House was established in 1639 in the present-day Quincy Area, and by 1640 the town was
        renamed Braintree. This Meeting House was the site of the original church, which first
        gathered on September 10, 1707. In 1708, old Braintree was divided into the North Precinct
        (Quincy) and the South Precinct (Braintree). When Quincy became an official town in 1792,
        the 1707 church was designated as the First Church in Braintree. The records in this
        collection include the journal of Samuel Niles dating 1697 to 1777, a volume of church
        records dating from 1707-1871, a volume of the Braintree Precinct's Financial Records dating
        1708 to 1796, and a volume of church records dating 1790 to 1825.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="n88093595" source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Congregational Church (Braintree, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="n85277127" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Niles, Samuel, 1674-1762</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_90d97ac1f88e57df01c3f9e9d70ad74b">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_df6b1ad0e1453981f02a85a17a858edb">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_27c40545a3f296ea22148219abfb79cd">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Braintree, Mass. First Congregational Church records,
        1697-1871. RG5302. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_345c7b336b007f3c28443fbaa37600a2">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>All materials besides "church records, 1707-1871" were temporarily deposited for
        digitization with the Congregational Library &amp; Archives by the First Congregational
        Church in Braintree in November 2015; no accession number.</p>
      <p>Church records, 1707-1871 were temporarily deposited for digitization with the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives by the First Congregational Church in Braintree in
        November 2018; 2018-37.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <originalsloc id="aspace_6d541e49a19f0f8094991721fc5c0e8e">
      <head>Location of Originals</head>
      <p>The physical records are held and maintained by the First Congregational Church in
        Braintree, Massachusetts.</p>
    </originalsloc>
    <accruals id="aspace_770082dca7775ea98b40dca21ba32443">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_b1042cf5576b229fe267bcf5435020c9">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Corinne Bernstein, February 2016, using DACS Second Edition. Collection
        re-described by Jules Thomson in January 2020 to reflect accrual of 1707-1871 volume of
        church records.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_245fd0f08b86ba576f39326e697811ed">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The first Parish to settle in the Braintree area in 1634 was known as "Mount Wollaston,"
        named after the founder of a trading post in 1624. The Mount Wollaston Parish Meeting House
        was established in 1639 in the present-day Quincy Area, and by 1640 the town was renamed
        Braintree. Braintree originally included present-day Braintree, Quincy, Randolph, and
        Holbrook. The Parish Meeting House was the site of the original church, which first gathered
        on September 10, 1707. In 1708, old Braintree was divided into the North Precinct (Quincy)
        and the South Precinct (Braintree). At the time, Braintree was sometimes referred to as
        "Monatiquot," after the Massachusett Indian village and home of Chief Wompatuck. When Quincy
        became an official town in 1792, the 1707 church was designated as the First Church in
        Braintree. Over the years, the church has been known as the First Congregational Church,
        Christ Church, and the Church of the Presidents. The first ministers of the church included
        Hugh Adams (ordained 1707), Samuel Niles (ordained 1711), and Ezra Weld (ordained 1762).</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_418abe420e4bde1709c2bed9aa8a0d51">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>The records from the First Congregational Church in Braintree, Mass. document the history
        of the organization, Braintree Precinct, and Pastor Samuel Niles, including membership,
        finances, church life, and the thoughts of the Pastor. Included in the records are meeting
        minutes, financial records, journal entries, and lists of marriages, baptisms, deaths, and
        admissions to the church.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_f89d35dac34bd27300365bd8c2908d1a">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The four volumes are arranged chronologically by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_d74d8aba7736d2c2582f604c3f70ed33">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and alter, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_073d16ad3be7b9cd7c74228e72547c3a">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>By Richard S. Storrs, D.D: American slavery, and the means of removal: a sermon, preached
        in the First Congregational Church, Braintree, April 4, 1844. (28.9.4 1534)</p>
      <p>By First Congregational Church (Braintree, Mass.): Braintree, MA: First Congregational
        Church. (1907) (17.11.1 B73.4 FIRCC)</p>
      <p>By A. A. Ellsworth: Christian unity: a sermon preached at the First Parish Church,
        Braintree, Mass. (1895) (15.5 5834.1)</p>
      <p>By Rev. Richard S. Storrs: Continuance in the ministry: a discourse delivered in the First
        Congregational Church, Braintree, Mass., July 3, 1861, by Rev. Richard S. Storrs, on the
        fiftieth anniversary of his ordination. (15.4 5846 STOO-STOR)</p>
      <p>Compiled by Ruth W. Shuster: Gathered in 1707: a history of the First Congregational
        Church, Braintree, Massachusetts, 1707-1957. (1957) (17.11.1 B73.4 FIRCC GS 1957)</p>
      <p>By the pastor, Rev. A.A. Ellsworth: Law and order: a sermon preached at the First Parish
        Church, Braintree, Mass., on Sunday, April 5, 1891.) (15.4 5846 ELL-ELY)</p>
      <p>By Rev. Richard S. Storrs, D.D.: The pastor's farewell benediction. A sermon delivered in
        the First Congregational Church of Braintree, Mass., July 2, 1871, the day following being
        the sixtieth anniversary of his settlement, July 3, 1811, / (1871) (15.0.5 5621 S-TE)</p>
      <p>By Ebenezer Gay, A.M.: The untimely death of a man of God lamented: in a sermon preach'd at
        the funeral of the Reverend Mr. John Hancock, pastor of the First Church of Christ in
        Braintree, who died May 7th. 1744, aetatis suae 42. (1744) (15.0.7 5625 HAL-HAZ)</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025649" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church membership.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Diaries.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85081512" source="lcsh">
        <part>Marriage records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="n88093595" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Congregational Church (Braintree, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <persname identifier="n85277127" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Niles, Samuel, 1674-1762</part>
      </persname>
      <corpname identifier="n79023328" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Braintree (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_c6ea2828edc8dbcfe01283887d1c02c3" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Samuel Niles journal</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1697">1697</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1777">1777</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1697-1777</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_62a1b02e0ee86740c26d3b1664401b1d">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>The entries in this journal, dating from 1697 to 1777, document the Pastor, Samuel
            Niles', thoughts and activities within the church as well as the organizational and
            membership history of the First Congregational church of Braintree. The journal includes
            entries regarding the Covenant of Redemption, the Episcopacy, the Godhead of the Christ,
            the Protestant Power, the Papal Power, the 1665 plague in London, and the Pastor's work,
            "A Prospect of Death- A Pindarique Essay," written on March 19, 1721. Also included in
            the entries is the Pastor's own account of his birth, wives, children, marriages, and
            ordination.</p>
          <p>The volume also includes records of the marriages, baptisms, and members admitted into
            communion, which the Pastor oversaw. On page 48, there is a written history of Samuel
            Niles. The records also include the Abington church covenant that was in place during
            Niles' ministry, records of burials near the Braintree church meeting house, Niles'
            financial account with the church and a list of the Churches of Christ living in
            December of 1777.</p>
          <p>Although the journal does not include mention of the Stamp Act, the son of the
            journal's author, Deacon Samuel Niles, was the chairman of a committee of five from
            Braintree enlisted to draft instructions for the townspeople to react to the Act in
            1765. This committee commissioned John Adams "to draft the documents recounting the
            freedoms expected by American colonists," which became the Braintree Instructions. Forty
            more Massachusetts towns endorsed the Braintree Instructions, a precursor of the
            American Revolution. The Stamp Act was repealed a year later in the spring of 1766.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <altformavail id="aspace_5e9dbc3edefa8cf9d3f04dc62d9a48a5">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Braintree/viewer/Samuel20Niles27s20journal2C2016971777/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ae5f7ff64abcb1bce45e989700494288" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1708">1708</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1796">1796</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1708-1796</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_28168886a25fe480513235bda84b1936">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>The records in this volume document the financial and organizational history of the
            Braintree District from 1708 to 1796. The records include the Precinct's meeting
            minutes, financial records, bills of credit and credit payments. Meeting minutes include
            discussion to build the new Precinct meeting house, beginning on page 82, a list of
            citizens who bought the thirty-six pews of the new meeting house on pages 93-94, and a
            report of the Precinct lines being drawn on page 128.</p>
          <p>The different names used to refer to the Precinct within the records also reflect the
            evolution of the Braintree region. From pages 1 to 24 the area is referred to as the
            "South Precinct," from pages 25 to 27 it is referred to as "the South or Middle
            precinct", from pages 28 to 192 it is referred to as the "Middle Precinct," from pages
            193 to 200 it is referred to as the "First Precinct, formerly the Middle Precinct," and
            from page 201 onward the region is referred to as the "Braintree Precinct."</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <altformavail id="aspace_e9f9805e65a38eb97548684fc48f4a82">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Braintree/viewer/Financial20records2C2017081796/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_a8a25b2f4dbc8f2e6aef121525654f09" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1707">1707</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1871">1871</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1707-1871</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_ce8a98d7df4dc728dc55b41c70f6cb84">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This bound volume comprises the earliest church records, with some apparently copied
            from a previous version, as well as later records continuing to 1871. The front cover
            label on the volume reads: "Copy of Older Record Book and Dr. Storrs' Record Book." It
            contains meeting minutes, lists of members, baptisms, marriages, deaths, a copy of the
            church covenant, and copies of official correspondence.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <altformavail id="aspace_8f38702054f62bc9b4db0e90a26d94ef">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Braintree/viewer/Church20records2C2017071871/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_247bd8a9add6890670a82b72d670c11d" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1790">1790</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1825">1825</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1790-1825</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_9785f679fe5ec83e79fc7088cb4c4fe4">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>Two sets of records were kept within this volume, and are presented here consecutively
            for ease of use. The first set of records includes lists of the church's minsters and
            members, covenants, and meeting minutes. The second set of records contains lists of
            baptisms, marriages, deaths, and admissions to the church. This volume is stated to be a
            direct continuation of Samuel Niles's Journal, which he originally took with him to
            Abington when he left this church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <altformavail id="aspace_6badc7e424930c1dd7088eeb25f3a455">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Braintree/viewer/Church20records2C2017621824/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
