<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/CambridgeMASecond-0833.xml"
      >CambridgeMASecond-0833</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/CambridgeMASecond-0833.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Cambridge, Mass. Second Church covenant, 1739.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-04-30</date>
        <num>RG0833</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-04-30T19:17:20+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday April 30,
          2019 at 19:17</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Cambridge, Mass. Second Church covenant, 1739.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG0833</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>1</quantity>
        <unittype>Folder</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <datesingle standarddate="1739">1739</datesingle>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <abstract id="aspace_7889ce3b1c753d0048498e8b8d63aee6">In 1725, citing the long distance
        required to attend worship services, a group of parishioners from the First Church of Christ
        in Cambridge requested that a precinct be formed in Menotomy village, now Arlington. This
        request was granted in 1732 and the Second Church of Cambridge was formaly gathered in 1739.
        This collection contains the original covenant of the Second Church in Cambridge. which was
        created during the formation of the church.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="n97093202" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Second Church (Cambridge, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_375b3cc9e6620b7a7adceb81fe8f2881">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_e59f5c3ead810d9ee6cf70acb54ca4bc">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_ca41a610663e78179f6e8b731f7e0b5f">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Cambridge, Mass. Second Church covenant, 1739, RG0833. The
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_3e7817353fa31236e26f445bef51c06b">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>No acquisition information is available for this collection.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accruals id="aspace_e96b5820fed335c5ed30b31d519cf7c3">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_8b7067fe36cba0c9713eb3dcef03e51d">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Zachary Bodnar, April 2019, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_33fe52dbf9ac115057d8be6963f47ed3">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The town of Arlington, Massachusetts, was originally a village within the boundaries of
        Cambridge named <emph render="italic">Menotomy</emph>, an Algonquin word meaning "swift
        running water." In 1725, citing the long distance required to attend worship services, a
        group of parishioners from the First Church of Christ in Cambridge requested that a precinct
        be formed in Menotomy so that a new church could be gathered. This initial request was
        denied. Subsequent requests were brought to the General Court and in 1732 they ruled that
        Menotomy would become the Norwest Precinct of Cambridge. Construction on the first
        meetinghouse was completed in 1734. In 1735 the search for a permanent minister was begun;
        the search did not end until 1739 when Rev. Samuel Cook agreed to become the first minister.
        With Rev. Cook installed, the church was formally gathered on September 9, 1739.</p>
      <p>In 1805 the second meeting house was constructed. Two years later, in 1805, Manotomy
        village was incorporated as the independent town of West Cambridge. In 1829 the church
        called Rev. Frederick Hodge, a Unitarian. In the wake of Hodge's installation, some members
        left the parish on order to form the Pleasant Street Congregational Church. In 1833 there
        was a parish meeting where a resolution to designate the church as Universalist was
        introduced and passed. The following week, another meeting took place and the previous
        resolution was overturned. The split in the parish led to those advocating a conversion to
        Universalism leaving the parish to form their own church. The third meeting house was
        constructed in 1840. That meeting house was destroyed in a fire on January 1, 1855.
        Construction on the fourth meeting house was completed that same year. The meeting house
        drew on Victorian architectural design and included a steeple; the town paid for the steeple
        to include, in its design, a clock with four faces.</p>
      <p>In 1867 the town of West Cambridge was renamed to Arlington; at that time the name of the
        church was changed to First Congregational Church in Arlington. Throughout the latter half
        of the nineteenth-century, and well into the twentieth century, the parish community was
        largely split between conservative and progressive factions; this resulted in the short
        ministerial services of a number of pastors during this time. In 1961 the Unitarian and
        Universalist denominations merged. As a result, First Church and the Universalist church,
        which had split from First in 1833, began to talk of reuniting the churches. That merge
        happened in 1965 and the church was renamed to the First Parish Unitarian Universalist
        Church. In 1975 the fourth meeting house was destroyed in a fire. The fifth, and final,
        meeting house, was constructed shortly thereafter.</p>
      <p>The First Parish Unitarian Universalist Church in Arlington continues to serve the local
        community today.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_b5ddfbb59f19c85982588e6e42d224e1">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains the original covenant of the Second Church in Cambridge. The
        covenant was created during the formation of the church in 1739 and includes the tenants
        that would be upheld by members of the church and a list of names of the original
        members.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <phystech id="aspace_36c5895c762fa7e26eb7096e08ddfe7c">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <bibliography id="aspace_5a4ec9285bcca2e59e5ad5178cc0c0eb">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Shriver, Diane Taraz. "On This Corner." Sermon presented at the First Parish Unitarian
        Universalist Church, Arlington, MA, February 7, 2016. <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.firstparish.info/PDFDownloads/history/on_this_corner_sermon.pdf"
          linktitle="On This Corner" show="new"
          >http://www.firstparish.info/PDFDownloads/history/on_this_corner_sermon.pdf</ref>.</p>
      <p>Shriver, Diane Taraz. "Opening the Doors." Sermon presented at the First Parish Unitarian
        Universalist Church, Arlington, MA, May 7, 2017. <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.firstparish.info/PDFDownloads/history/opening_the_doors_sermon.pdf"
          linktitle="Opening the Doors" show="new"
          >http://www.firstparish.info/PDFDownloads/history/opening_the_doors_sermon.pdf</ref>.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="n82018575" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Arlington (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n79061258" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Cambridge (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n97093202" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Second Church (Cambridge, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="nr93041638" source="lcnaf">
        <part>West Cambridge (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_2dd3905ef9fb2c4f497da5584ab30949" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Covenant</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1739">1739</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_13d5a84da4f2d46a538a1326eb7b309c" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_c1f801c62ab639e25142b4afa6891115" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_13d5a84da4f2d46a538a1326eb7b309c">5</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_e833195cf00792abf187b2ac7a12b31a">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>This church record was digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project.
            Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/CambridgeSecond/viewer/ChurchCovenant1739/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
