<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/HaverhillMAWest-5067.xml"
      >HaverhillMAWest-5067</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/HaverhillMAWest-5067.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Haverhill, Mass. West Congregational Church records, 1734-1900.</titleproper>
        <author>Jules Thomson</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-10-15</date>
        <num>RG5067</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition (DACS)</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-10-15T15:49:27+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday October 15,
          2019 at 15:49</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Haverhill, Mass. West Congregational Church records, 1734-1900.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5067</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library and Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>.44</quantity>
        <unittype>Cubic Feet</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(1 box)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1734">1734</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1900">1900</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1734-1900</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_a19e3ea0ebffaeba0bbd20c68ee663a8">When the western part of Haverhill
        became too populous for one church in 1734, the West Parish of Haverhill was established by
        a petition to the General Court of Massachusetts, and the church, initially known as the
        Third Church, was itself established in 1735. In the first half of the 19th century, the
        governance of the parish was controversially distributed between multiple denominations, but
        in 1852 it was relinquished again to the Congregationalists. This collection contains the
        earliest records of the West Congregational Church and continuing administrative
        documentation up until 1900.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname rules="rda" source="local">
          <part>Third Church (Haverhill, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname rules="rda" source="naf">
          <part>West Congregational Church (Haverhill, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_cdffadd1efcbc2b7ef365e4214818848">
      <head> Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_b1b66f0ceaa717aaf932c84c6d8507d6">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_fc67da2921c1ac6ebf0560f2c54c297f">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Haverhill, Mass. West Congregational Church records,
        1734-1900, RG5067. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_5809798aae1be1bfaa64faa0813c3d29">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Loaned to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives, for digitization, by the West Church
        in Haverhill, Massachusetts, March 2011; There is no accession number for this
        collection.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <originalsloc id="aspace_14edfc55f2541fd54e7ec6827533bcaf">
      <head>Location of Originals</head>
      <p>The physical records are held and maintained by the West Church in Haverhill,
        Massachusetts.</p>
    </originalsloc>
    <accruals id="aspace_b94f348acf63e2d29838e9fed2c0dc11">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_5a0b180826cd2f27c015fdb0f5c1bf55">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed and described by Jules Thomson, October 2019, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_5ecdbf2804bc41396c419887d32898af">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>When the western part of Haverhill became too populous for one church in 1734, the West
        Parish of Haverhill was established by a petition to the General Court of Massachusetts. 77
        members were dismissed from the First Parish Church and constructed a new meeting house,
        located "on the southeasterly corner of Samuel Eatton's pasture". The building, which was
        intended for both secular and religious use, was dedicated on Oct. 22, 1735. After two trial
        preachers, the church successfully settled and ordained the Rev. Samuel Bachellor, a Harvard
        graduate, in July of 1735. During his ministry 118 new members were admitted to the
        church.</p>
      <p>In 1738, soon after the Parish was incorporated, the committee acquired land to be used for
        a burying-ground and roads. In 1739, the parish voted to gift Rev. Bachellor all the
        parsonage lands belonging to the West Parish, in addition to 70 acres which he had already
        been gifted by town proprietors. The parish committee also granted Rev. Bachellor several
        additions to his salary over the years, in order to offset currency depreciation which was
        endemic in mid-18th-century New England. Rev. Bachellor also owned at least one slave,
        identified in a death record of March 24, 1785 only as "Nero, servant to ye Revd Mr
        Bachellor." Theological differences between Rev. Bachellor and his congregation led to
        increasing strife within the church. In 1755, a number of congregants led by Mr. Joseph
        Haynes accused him of heresy, specifically for alleging in a sermon that Christ had declared
        that the work of redemption was "finished" during the crucifixion. He was ultimately removed
        in October of 1761 after ongoing disputes. After his dismissal the parish was without a
        settled pastor for 9 years.</p>
      <p>In 1762 the church and parish voted to adopt the Cambridge Platform of church discipline.
        In the same year Rev. Nathaniel Noyes was called to the ministry after a trial period, but
        ultimately declined, as did subsequent trial ministers until March, 1769, when "a great
        majority" of the parish voted to invite Rev. Phineas Adams to the ministry. Rev. Adams was
        eventually ordained in January of 1771. He continued in the role until his death in 1801. In
        1751 the parish voted to build a schoolhouse, though construction did not occur until 1791.
        In 1770, the parish voted "to continue to sing Dr. Watts' Psalms &amp; Hymns in the
        congregation." This is the first allusion to singing in the parish records, and there is
        also mention of a "Singers Pew" which was enlarged in 1788 and again in 1794. In 1810 the
        parish approved 13 dollars toward the support of a singing school.</p>
      <p>After the death of Rev. Adams in 1801, the parish was without a settled minister for 25
        years. This was exacerbated by a substantial change in the organization of the parish in the
        early 1800s, in which Baptist, Methodist, and Universalist residents increasingly shared
        governance. In 1806 it was voted to divide the parish funds between the different
        denominations based on their respective tax contributions, and in 1809 a committee composed
        of one representative each from the Congregationalist, Methodist, and Universalist
        denominations was appointed to oversee the division of parish funds. Discord followed in the
        wake of these structural changes. In 1818, the Congregationalists attempted to regain
        control of the entire parish but were unsuccessful. From 1821-1824 the parish attempted to
        settle three different ministers, none of which were ultimately approved by the
        Congregationalists.</p>
      <p>Finally, in September, 1826, the church unanimously invited the Congregationalist Rev.
        Moses Grosvenor to the ministry. The parish approved the decision, and Mr. Grosvenor
        accepted the invitation and was ordained in December of 1826. The other denominations within
        the parish remained unsatisfied, and petitioned in 1828 for money to hire additional
        ministers. The parish committee ruled 50-53 against their request, but subsequently voted to
        dismiss Rev. Grosvenor, with "three months' notice to withdraw his pastoral connection". The
        Congregationalists then decided to withdraw and organize a new society. This division
        created a distinct Parish (Universalist) Society and a Church (Congregationalist) Society, a
        state of affairs which lasted from 1828-1852. The Church Society built a new brick meeting
        house one mile west of the old parish meeting house', and in 1829 petitioned the parish to
        settle the Rev. Abijah Cross of Salisbury, New Hampshire. The request was granted and Rev.
        Cross accepted and was installed in 1831. In 1832, it was voted to move the old meeting
        house 1.25 miles west to the center of the parish, which was accomplished by 1834.</p>
      <p>In 1852, after protracted arguments between the Parish and Church societies over the
        allocation of endowments, the parish was transferred back to the Congregationalists and the
        Universalist society was re-organized as The First Universalist Society in the West Parish
        of Haverhill. In 1853, Rev. Cross was dismissed from the Congregational church and society
        at his own request, and Rev. Asa Farwell was subsequently settled as pastor. During his
        pastorate, 86 new members were admitted, many of them during an 1863 religious revival
        brought on by the turmoil of the Civil War. After Rev. Farwell was dismissed in 1866, Rev.
        Ephraim Allen was settled as pastor and remained in the position until 1876. In 1874-5 the
        meeting house was extensively remodeled at a cost of about 9,000 dollars.</p>
      <p>The church was officially incorporated in 1921. It is now known as West Congregational
        Church, and continues to serve the Haverhill community as a member of the Conservative
        Congregational Christian Conference (CCCC).</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_aa95f6826b6a52908ac525860833cb0b">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains the earliest records of the West Congregational Church, and
        continuing administrative documentation up until 1900. including the articles of agreement
        for the construction of the first meeting house, administrative records, membership
        information, and financial accounting. There is also a "new building book" containing
        records relating to the construction of the second meetinghouse in 1828.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_80ac7873f62bef4f513c567611aece39">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection has been arranged in chronological order by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_195f73083a9cee89a5fe9fc98bbde647">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <bibliography id="aspace_88a07bf3bf4a1ecaf7a9e4aa1c1c7f52">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p><emph>Excercises Commemorative of the One Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the West
          Congregational Church, Haverhill, Mass.</emph> Haverhill: C. C. Morse &amp; Son, 1886.
        17.11.1 H29.45 WESCC</p>
      <p>Chase, George Wingate. <emph>The history of Haverhill, Massachusetts, from its first
          settlement, in 1640, to the year 1860.</emph> Haverhill: George W. Chase, 1861.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85000938" source="lcsh">
        <part>Admonition.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025597" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church discipline.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025649" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church membership.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85033612" source="lcsh">
        <part>Covenants (Church polity).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85081512" source="lcsh">
        <part>Marriage records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85090572" source="lcsh">
        <part>Necrologies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85095385" source="lcsh">
        <part>Ordination.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="n82020635" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Haverhill (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname rules="rda" source="local">
        <part>Third Church (Haverhill, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname rules="rda" source="naf">
        <part>West Congregational Church (Haverhill, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_f804779e5c1999cf1ae4e2a27aaaf7ce" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Articles of agreement</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1734">1734</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_a26bc4a9d14987bb038699312361c99b">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/Articles20of20Agreement2C201734/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_e6bd0665157747f6d7ff82f260841332">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This document details the plans and budget for the construction of the first
            meetinghouse in the West Parish.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_045258abc4c3f84dcef58647287e71ea" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Parish records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1734">1734</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1802">1802</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1734-1802</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_8020cfbd3ccc2424b4a8eb24bdbdf3d3">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/Church20records2C2017341802/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_bb35f2e12244930edd382059027ac495">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the earliest administrative and financial records of the Haverhill
            West parish and the Third Church, including the ordination of Samuel Bacheller, pew
            sales, the election of officers, and parish expenses.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_02da1495316393a6e3547aa418632a02" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1735">1735</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1761">1761</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1735-1761</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_da46ecd52cfb63b87787bc998b665df6">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/Church20records2C2017351761/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_28e1694f5f03d725f8d302dbafc08c5a">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume was kept by the Third Church's Rev. Stephen Bachellor. It primarily
            contains membership records, including baptisms, marriages, admissions, dismissions, and
            narrative accounts of several prominent families. It also contains the covenant signed
            by the founding members.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_655ae7e12f050841f3adba72d762945f" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1762">1762</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1826">1826</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1762-1826</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_75bb48fd92451121e58d799fd9bd3224">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/Church20records2C2017621826/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_23700901a8c33ad0a753e0cf20f4bbb5">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains membership records, transcribed correspondence, records of several
            disciplinary cases, and information about the ministers who served during these
            years.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_bb7039b81524aea88f8429a929793346" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Treasurer's book</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1815">1815</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1900">1900</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1815-1900</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_39fe9a3ddf1905525f2a467d269ea9df">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/Treasurer27s20book2C2018151900/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_6bfc4fa7060016c30957de13d0f61b58">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>The treasurer's ledger contains itemized records of the church's income and expenses,
            including taxes, pew fees, materials and labor for maintenance of the meetinghouse, and
            the minister's salary. There are regular audits of the church's accounts by the
            treasurers and committee members.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_c5e7cf62a26e46d7548debeff943ec5f" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1826">1826</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1838">1838</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1826-1838</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_6ed0e837fc0856093eb5262a7e851197">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/Church20records2C2018261838/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_adfa0b0e2339b7136d3e69da9e4ac250">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains interspersed administrative, financial, and membership
            records.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_372f0805f3443c12829e3a1914f49f7d" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>New building book</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1828">1828</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1852">1852</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1828-1852</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_f389cd17dc1a71a494c7b7873c47ddb7">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/New20building20book2C2018281852/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_a46703a9502f737d2d6ace373b16703b">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This book contains the planning and financial records relating to the construction of
            the church's second meetinghouse, as well as the annual renewal of Rev. Cross's
            contract. The end of the volume contains the will of David Webster, which includes
            provisions for a trust to pay the church's ministerial salary.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_1f3bf0a48f9ed5ee297c8bcd6a57f53d" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1870">1870</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1880">1880</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1870-1880</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_b69b81ac94b2f015adc1e13ff25d0b4b">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HaverhillWest/viewer/Church20records2C2018701880/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_8f00c544eec823c4ce2fd1f4a63bc132">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains interspersed administrative, financial, and membership records
            continuing from the previous books. It also includes several printed materials that have
            been sewn or glued into the book adjacent to the related records.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
