<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/HawleyGideon-1237.xml"
      >HawleyGideon-1237</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/HawleyGideon-1237.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Gideon Hawley missionary journals, 1753-1806.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2020-02-11</date>
        <num>MS1237</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS 2019.0.3</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2020-02-11T16:28:10+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday February 11,
          2020 at 16:28</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Gideon Hawley missionary journals, 1753-1806.</unittitle>
      <unitid>MS1237</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>0.65</quantity>
        <unittype>Cubic Feet</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(1 box, 5 reels)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1753">1753</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1806">1806</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1753-1806</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_7256b6af4b3b540b28bf1bbeaf93dd54">Rev. Gideon Hawley was born at
        Stratfield (Bridgeport), Connecticut. Hawley graduated from Yale College in 1749 and was
        licensed to preach by the Fairfield East Association May 1750. Hawley accepted a position
        from the Society for Propagating the Gospel among the Indians to establish a mission among
        the Six Nations on the Susquehanna in 1954. In 1757 Hawley was sent on a temporary mission
        to the Mashpee and following a formal request by the Mashpee Hawley took up a permanent post
        among them on April 8, 1758. Hawley died in Mashpee in 1807. This collection of journal and
        correspondence records includes materials relating to life in the Mohawk country, the Six
        Nations, the Mashpee Indians, and the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel among the
        Indians.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="n91082000" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Hawley, Gideon, 1727-1807</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_53c2d108f03c4ff6684d91508ae0e19d">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_5dfac266eeda1965adf9505451b0cb47">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_f3e20ba411d8fe51496920cc1babfd1a">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Gideon Hawley missionary journals, 1753-1806, MS1237. The
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_58d7a7bd9b6af63c6cd8d7061ed05eff">
      <head>Source of Acquisition</head>
      <p>The journals were gifted to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives by A. C. Thompson in
        1875; no accession number. The journals were originally cataloged with the call number M 11
        H 31.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <altformavail id="aspace_e7a20846393ac55944fbfb408826190a">
      <head>Location of Copies</head>
      <p>The Massachusetts Historical Society maintains their own copy of the microfilms. The
        microfilm was assigned the call number P-363 reel 8.1.</p>
    </altformavail>
    <accruals id="aspace_06d85056b92a596eca590b8fd7fa332a">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_20fcf849ccd3d6e609849e0739f3ab9f">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>This collection was originally cataloged as M 11 H 31 and placed within the library's
        holdings. The collection was first described by archival staff in 1996. The collection was
        redescribed by Sari Mauro, September 2013, using DACS First Edition. The collection was
        reprocessed by Zachary Bodnar, February 2020, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_58293c5e0cccd5bbde27686944b72435">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>Rev. Gideon Hawley was born at Stratfield (Bridgeport), Connecticut, the son of Gideon and
        Hannah Bennett Hawley. His mother, a daughter of Lieutenant James Bennett of Stratfield,
        Connecticut died at Hawley's birth. Hawley's father died when Hawley junior was three years
        old. Hawley was a descendent of Joseph Hawley, who immigrated to America in 1629.</p>
      <p>Hawley graduated from Yale College in 1749 and was licensed to preach by the Fairfield East
        Association May 1750. He accepted a position in Stockbridge in 1752, under the pay of the
        Society for Propagating the Gospel among the Indians and under the supervision of Jonathan
        Edwards. Jonathan Edwards was a preacher to the whites and the Housatonic Indians in the
        Stockbridge; he occasionally visited Hawley's school to the Iroquois and gave Hawley advice
        about his work with the Native Americans there.</p>
      <p>Due to "opposing cliques among the controlling authorities" at Stockbridge, Hawley accepted
        a position from the Society to establish a mission among the Six Nations on the Susquehanna;
        he was ordained in Old South Church, Boston, July 31, 1754 for this position and left for
        the site, near the contemporary town of Windsor, New York (close to the area where Rev.
        Elihu Spencer, Yale 1746, made an unsuccessful attempt at ministry five or six years
        before). Besides acting as a missionary, Rev. Hawley also acted as an interpreter at this
        post. War did not affect his mission until May 1756, when Hawley was forced to leave. He
        attempted to return to his former mission, but since it was unsafe, he remained in West
        Springfield, Massachusetts for the winter. He tried to rejoin his former congregation in the
        spring of 1757, but the prevalence of small pox prevented him from doing so.</p>
      <p>Hawley returned to Boston and accepted a commission as chaplain to Colonel Richard
        Gridley's regiment. He departed with the army for Crown Point July 12 but was forced to
        return in October, due to illness. The Society then sent Hawley on a temporary mission to
        the large plantation (approximately 300) of Native Americans at Mashpee, Massachusetts, who
        had been without a preacher for fifteen years. The Mashpee requested Hawley's permanent
        appointment; Hawley took up the permanent post April 8, 1758.</p>
      <p>In Mashpee, Hawley married Lucy Fessenden July 14, 1759, second daughter of Rev. Benjamin
        Fessenden (Harvard 1718) and Rebecca (Smith) Fessenden of Sandwich. Hawley and Fessenden had
        three sons and two daughters. The eldest son died in infancy, and other children all lived
        to maturity. The youngest son graduated at Harvard in 1792 and died in 1800, early on in his
        pastoral life. Lucy Fessenden died in December 25, 1777 at the age of 50 and Hawley
        remarried Mrs. Elizabeth Burchard October 7, 1778, widow of Captain David Burchard of
        Nantucket and previous widow of a Mr. Hussey. Mrs. Elizabeth Burchard was born in Mendon,
        Massachusetts October 12, 1726 and died August 7, 1797. Hawley died in Mashpee in 1807.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_803f2e749d6e3a52a83373aee91e009e">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>Items in this collection include correspondence, journal accounts, lists of births and
        deaths, a table of Native American statistics, and a map (1756) by Hawley of Onohoguage
        villages in New York. This collection includes materials relating to life in the Mohawk
        country, the Six Nations, the Mashpee Indians, the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel
        among the Indians, the Massachusetts General Court, and the French and Indian War. Persons
        named include James Abercromby, Jonathan Edwards, John Hancock, and William Johnson. Of
        particular note are records mentioning Hawley's long-time translator, Rebecca Kellogg
        Ashley.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_6c34a59dc6dc62ab1fb199b95d6ad08a">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection has been arranged in volume order which generally is also date order.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_60ca164c5a31744a38cee6c70c5602b8">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
      <p>A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader
        is available to the public upon request.</p>
    </phystech>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_da1ae5997965fa61330aaf211b2b487c">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>The Massachusetts Historical Society holds two archival collections related to Gideon
        Hawley. The "Gideon Hawley letters, 1754-1807" collection contains correspondence written by
        Gideon Hawley largely related to his missionary work and the "Letter to Gideon Hawley, April
        1764" contains a single letter written by Cognehew, Reuben to Gideon Hawley asking for
        additional funds for his Mashpee Indian school.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_03fc17e3354fdc018f0ea2b199b4de49">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Dexter, Franklin Bowditch. <emph render="italic">Biographical Sketches of the Graduates of
          Yale College with Annals of the College History.</emph> New York: Henry Hold and Company,
        1896.</p>
      <p>Malone, Dumas, ed. <emph render="italic">Dictionary of American Biography.</emph> New York:
        Charles Scribner's Sons, 1932.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Indians of North America -- Missions. </part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Mashpee Indians -- Missions. </part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Missionaries -- Massachusetts -- Biography.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85123612" source="lcsh">
        <part>Smallpox.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85128212" source="lcsh">
        <part>Stockbridge Indians -- Missions. </part>
      </subject>
      <geogname identifier="sh85140137" source="lcsh">
        <part>United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763.</part>
      </geogname>
      <persname identifier="n2009014655" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Ashley, Rebecca Kellogg, 1695-1757</part>
      </persname>
      <persname identifier="n79084179" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Edwards, Jonathan, 1703-1758</part>
      </persname>
      <persname identifier="n91082000" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Hawley, Gideon, 1727-1807 -- Diaries.</part>
      </persname>
      <persname identifier="n91082000" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Hawley, Gideon, 1727-1807 -- Correspondence.</part>
      </persname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_978f0df8cb4c2af073680a64c058c572" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1754">1754</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1756">1756</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1754-1756</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_d38bcdad650b31356ecd4152ecbf793e" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_132ef3fd4ab11c03d5c075d043977b07" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_d38bcdad650b31356ecd4152ecbf793e">1</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_2f81d6b53a6fd0dd8cee1b2bd81a56f2">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These journal records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HawleyGideon/viewer/Volume2012C2017541756/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_6666f9915e42f7e9cbf4152b177f988c">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>The first volume chronicles Rev. Hawley's time as a missionary traveling through "the
            Country of the Six Nations" which is now western New York and Pennsylvania. Rev. Hawley
            keep record of the villages he visited, the people he interacted with, and the Bible
            passages on which he preached.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_4f08ded7462115d5fd74d3180deffd43" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1753">1753</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1795">1795</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="inclusive">circa
            1753-1795</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_1596fb3a5dd6cbf1a840a18408d65efd" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_5a73059f38e4af4937b8747085575f1c" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_1596fb3a5dd6cbf1a840a18408d65efd">2</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail audience="internal" id="aspace_a0ccae59a5e1cfc9e7bd28644aafd5a4">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These journal records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HawleyGideon/viewer/Volume2022C20ca2017531795/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_762b93b71200b679c186a6e14a795e04">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>Rev. Hawley's second volume contains copies of correspondence referred to in vol. 1,
            financial records, and a continuation of his travelogue from "the Country of the Six
            Nations". His movements were often hampered by early battles in the French and Indian
            War, which he also described.</p>
          <p>The first few pages in this book contain a later 19th-century letter to a genealogist
            with a brief Hawley family history, and the 1875 inscription from A. C. Thompson when he
            donated the journals to the Congregational Library.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_9777e972208f9c338be04e34dae1b108" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1777">1777</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1806">1806</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="inclusive">circa
            1777-1806</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_d676f660896966e4c6a7afde334775bd" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_6576bf2fef3963827c4f9c348f65d56c" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_d676f660896966e4c6a7afde334775bd">3</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_bba9879528182af01138ab2d58380bfa">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These journal records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HawleyGideon/viewer/Volume2032C20ca2017771806/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_4f3307f21162da0f31da0dc0e8a63dad">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>The third volume is largely comprised of correspondence to friends and officials back
            in New England. Rev. Hawley advocates for better treatment of both their Native American
            neighbors and lower-class English soldiers. There are also sections in which Hawley
            reflects on his missionary career, providing further detail about the events recorded in
            vols. 1 &amp; 2.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_2346f9916b9bff590e987c6bae9bb266" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1781">1781</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1806">1806</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="inclusive">circa
            1781-1806</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_d3646a9935d25fe5fe3e3269fde04341" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_bfb24a6f8ff15909353eb5281224de5e" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_d3646a9935d25fe5fe3e3269fde04341">4</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_d81277f95682b34c7935d59e89431ffd">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These journal records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/HawleyGideon/viewer/Volume2042C20ca2017811806/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_acfa22030a2f07084d217a55acc0e359">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This fourth volume is primarily correspondence. The topics range from the fates of
            indentured Mashpee Indians to friends' legal matters to his own personal finances. Rev.
            Hawley also recorded local births, deaths, and marriages at the Mashpee plantation for
            much of the latter half of the 18th century.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_361f3f7a882e5a5c04fd4349edb0383a" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Microfilm records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1753">1753</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1806">1806</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1753-1806</unitdate>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1981">1981</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="2008">2008</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_841a98b8aaf21d4c77eb0512b49855f8" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >1 (positive)</container>
          <container id="aspace_26cadfe3a60123c2145f56476b76f632" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >2 (positive)</container>
          <container id="aspace_bc9c2a2ce5b8ddd1816dc5e7a0acf9a7" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >3 (positive)</container>
          <container id="aspace_764ec910508ee1d7c0c9bde31481a59e" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >4 (negative)</container>
          <container id="aspace_e76b7de28227aaff28b7c1ba7d8e3f6b" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >5 (negative)</container>
        </did>
        <accessrestrict id="aspace_3b8b817c6bf98edf2872b5fb5a45eacd">
          <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
          <p>Reels 1 and 3 are available for use in the reading room. Reels 2, 4, and 5 are
            maintained as preservation copies and are not available for public use.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_fe7c6a66688ffd8f8aa67cfa85385d38">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>There are a total of five microfilm copies of the Gideon Hawley journals and each copy
            contains the full text of all four volumes. Two positive reels (reels 1 and 3) were
            produced by Harvard in 1981. Three additional reels (reels 2, 4, and 5), one positive
            and two negative, were produced by the Northeast Document Conservation Center in
            2008.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
