<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/IpswichMASouth-5298.xml"
      >IpswichMASouth-5298</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/IpswichMASouth-5298.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Ipswich, Mass. South Church records, 1747-1868.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar, Marya Shotkoski</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2017-11-06</date>
        <num>RG5298</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English </language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-05-31T13:19:11+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Friday May 31, 2019
          at 13:19</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="revised"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-05-30</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="human"/>
        <agent/>
        <eventdescription>Zachary Bodnar: Revised finding aid instances, notes, agents, title
          fields, and subjects using the current implementation of the processing
          manual.</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Ipswich, Mass. South Church records, 1747-1868.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5298</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="materialtype">
        <quantity>2</quantity>
        <unittype>Volumes</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="bulk">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1747">1747</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1868">1868</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="bulk"
        >1747-1868</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_a014a19d857f8ee01d479f61f94a2fca">The South Church in Ipswich,
        Massachusetts, was formally gathered in 1747 following ministerial angst between Ipswich's
        two ministers and a petition by parishioners in southern Ipswich who felt traveling to the
        First Church was too difficult. The first meeting house was completed in 1748 and
        construction on the second meeting house was completed in 1838. In 1922 the South Church
        rejoined the First Church to become the First and South Congregational Church. The South
        Church records document the history of the church through collected vital member records,
        church and parish meeting minutes, committee reports, and financial records.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="no98062004" source="lcnaf">
          <part>South Church (Ipswich, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_92b52c32ff4cae736ca9ca38782c0292">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_57b709ada3909ba6fa2f8d6232a3e166">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_269dd2977cb0523264f7957fad111346">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Ipswich, Mass. South Church records, 1747-1868. RG5298.
        The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_c791eb89b2477e8c622044bc38ed85d5">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Materials were temporarily loaned to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives, October 2015,
        by the First Church in Ipswich; Accession 2015-19.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <originalsloc id="aspace_291dee2ba02da8a0c006443fd730a751">
      <head>Location of Originals</head>
      <p>The original volumes are currently held by the First Church in Ipswich, Massachusetts,
        UCC.</p>
    </originalsloc>
    <accruals id="aspace_d83ed87f760106ea1dbad574900c8018">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_e0854fad62f4ab33c7c998d4685efccd">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Marya Shotkoski, October 2015, using DACS Second Edition. Additional
        processing and description by Zachary Bodnar, November 2017, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_305dc2197157574a1e8c6e39beb236d2">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The initial plan to create a new church "South side of the river" in Ipswich,
        Massachusetts, dates to a petition presented to the First Church in Ipswich in 1725. The
        primary reason cited in the petition for the creation of a south meeting house was the long
        and difficult travel parishioners in southern Ipswich had to overcome in order to attend the
        First Church. The Parish voted to allow for construction of a south meeting house; however,
        this did not come to pass, apparently, in part, because one of the two employed ministers,
        Rev. John Rogers, was quite popular.</p>
      <p>Calls for separation did not resume until 1746, shortly after the death of John Rogers in
        December, 1745. In 1746 a new petition for the creation of a south meeting house was
        presented to the First Parish. The new petition, beyond citing the geographic distance
        between communities, cited the fact that by 1746 the First Church meetinghouse was
        physically too small to comfortably accommodate the whole parish. Initially this petition
        was voted down. In 1746, Rev. John Walley was invited to become the second minister of the
        First Church to replace John Rogers. The first minister, Rev. Nathaniel Rogers and Rev.
        Walley did not get along well. When the disagreements between the two ministers became
        public, the First Parish voted to allow for the formation of a south meeting house and
        parish in large part to deescalate the feud between the two ministers. In 1747 the South
        Church was formally gathered and Rev. John Walley was installed as the first minister of the
        new church. Construction on the South Meeting House began in 1747 and was completed in the
        spring of 1748.</p>
      <p>In 1838, the second meeting house of the South Church was constructed. Rev. Thomas F.
        Waters, minister of the South Church from 1879-1919, organized the Ipswich Historical
        Society. In 1899 the church steeple was struck by lightning; while the church building
        survived the subsequent fire, the original bell did not. A new bell was secured by Elizabeth
        M. Brown in honor of her late husband, William G. Brown.</p>
      <p>In 1922 the South Church, whose membership had waned significantly in the
        twentieth-century, reformed with the First Church to form the First and South Congregational
        Church of Ipswich, Massachusetts. The South Church Meeting House was repurposed as the
        Parish House and served as that function until it was destroyed by fire in 1977. Only the
        bell survived the fire. The church lot was converted into a small park and the bell was
        repurposed into a memorial within the park. The First and South Congregational Church, now
        simply First Church, still serves the Ipswich community today.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_12d13799aad5f71465812146ba931a89">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>The South Church records document the history church and parish through collected member
        records, meeting minutes, committee reports, and financial records. Included in the
        collection are marriage records, baptismal records, records of deaths, membership lists,
        records detailing relations with the First Church, burial grounds records, and records
        related to music during church services.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_e97ade7b66324ecabd7b159a53e0f58b">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged chronologically by end date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_c5e7fbe0a379fbb1cf6528c1358a2dd8">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and alter, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_4bbc61d0b849d643618efe354d44768d">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>The Congregational Library &amp; Archives has digitized materials from the First Church in
        Ipswich and made <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/nehh/series1/IpswichMAFirst5288"
          linktitle="available to view online" show="new">them available to view online</ref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_b22a3be1e5e89b82c9ebab915093426e">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Water, Thomas Franklin. <emph render="italic">An Historical Address delivered on the 140th
          Anniversary of the Organization of the South Church, Ipswich, Sunday, July 31,
        1887</emph>. Ipswich: South Church, 1887. 17.11.1 I68.7 FrC</p>
      <p>Harris, Gordon. "South Congregational Church: Only the Bell Remains." Last modified
        February 6, 2019. <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="https://historicipswich.org/2019/02/06/south-church/" linktitle="link to article"
          show="new">https://historicipswich.org/2019/02/06/south-church/</ref>.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85066724" source="lcsh">
        <part>Installation (clergy).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85081512" source="lcsh">
        <part>Marriage records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85088919" source="lcsh">
        <part>Music in churches.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85090572" source="lcsh">
        <part>Necrologies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85100506" source="lcsh">
        <part>Pews and pew rights.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="n82058914" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Ipswich (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="no98062004" source="lcnaf">
        <part>South Church (Ipswich, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_621714d6319fbe2489f8d28a1436dd7e" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>South Parish Book of Records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1747">1747</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1851">1851</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1747-1851</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_46d007df18aa064ee3072a146813ffb3">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/IpswichSouth/viewer/Parish20records2C2017471851/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_954ba24a0dcfc97d76faff07db7f4a68">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the church history of the South Parish from 1747 to 1851 and
            includes the minutes of parish meetings and records of votes. Included within the
            records are pew deeds and pew chart, the development of the meeting house, payments to
            church officials and minister salaries, church appointments, their relationship with the
            First Church, committee records, parish affairs, burial grounds records, taxes
            collections, and the question of music in the church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_da7ff22184c2375ed1fc9cd1fc7a331d" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>South Parish record book</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1747">1747</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1868">1868</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1747-1868</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_3a59535ed4e35e99855ed221e0382e3f">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/IpswichSouth/viewer/Parish20records2C2017471868/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_f5bafd8ece401016801ba533a8a49565">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume is largely a church history of the South Parish from 1747 to 1868 and
            includes the South Parish covenant from 1747 as well as other founding documents.
            Additional records include parish meeting minutes, vital statistics such as births,
            baptisms, admissions, and marriages along with deaths, arranged by year, and membership
            lists by gender.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
