<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/IpswichMAFirst-5288.xml"
      >IpswichMAFirst-5288</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/IpswichMAFirst-5288.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Ipswich, Mass. First Church records, 1724-1898. </titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar, Marya Shotkoski</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-07-02</date>
        <num>RG5288</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>Portions of this collection are part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital
          historical representations of these portions of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English </language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-07-02T19:48:02+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday July 2, 2019
          at 19:48</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Ipswich, Mass. First Church records, 1724-1898.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5288</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>7</quantity>
        <unittype>Files</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(4 folders, 3 volumes)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1724">1724</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1898">1898</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1724-1898</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_769d6546b34a5468a2ba4d45622fa320">Ipswich, Massachusetts, first known as
          <emph render="italic">Agawam</emph>, was settled by John Winthrop in 1633 and was
        incorporated the following year. The First Church in Ipswich was gathered on August 5, 1634,
        and the first meeting house was constructed the same year. Construction on the second
        meeting house was completed in 1647. In 1699 the third meeting house of the First Church was
        built on the north green. Members left to form new churches in 1681, 1714, 1747, and 1749.
        In 1749 the fourth meeting house was constructed. David T. Kimball was ordained as the
        fourteenth minister of the First Church in Ipswich on October 3, 1806. Construction on the
        fifth meeting house was completed by 1847. The South Church in Ipswich voted to reunite with
        the First Church in Ipswich in 1922. In 1965 the fifth meeting house was destroyed by a fire
        and the sixth meeting house was completed in 1971. Now a member of the United Church of
        Christ, the First Church in Ipswich continues to serve the local community today. This
        collection contains the early church and parish records of the First Church in Ipswich and
        includes meeting minutes, financial records, and vital membership records. This collection
        also contains records and correspondence kept by Rev. David T. Kimball.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="no2014085949" source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Church (Ipswich, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="n85818236" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Kimball, David T. (David Tenney), 1782-1860</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_232cd2318814301ebbf0e3f2215cd7a4">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_fdde7f5cc8ac6c14ad0eda144af3dcbb">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_8b2f4e40833354cfa5444dbc66fdb14c">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Ipswich, Mass. First Church records, 1724-1898. RG5288.
        The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_1568d7030ec748e7fdde480815e72113">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>The David T. Kimball papers were donated to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives,
        October 2014, by Michael Moran; accession 2014-79. Originally given identifier RG5232.</p>
      <p>The record books were temporarily loaned to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives,
        2015, by the First Church in Ipswich, Massachusetts, UCC; accession 2015-19.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <originalsloc id="aspace_cf1111c9b97677094df49e8f97604e3f">
      <head>Location of Originals</head>
      <p>The physical record books are currently held by the First Church in Ipswich, Massachusetts,
        UCC.</p>
    </originalsloc>
    <accruals id="aspace_71ec0c17ea3df59a43409953aed625f3">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_83e4ba28342d6280e5ed8199a04c7885">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Marya Shotkoski, October 2015, using DACS Second Edition. Additional
        processing and finding aid work by Zachary Bodnar, November 2017. Merged with Ipswich, Mass.
        First Church records, 1808-1863, RG5232, and redescribed by Zachary Bodnar, July 2019, using
        DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_7d18a6ebcf887fc353ad4034ae820525">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>Ipswich, Massachusetts, first known as <emph render="italic">Agawam</emph>, was settled by
        John Winthrop, and twelve companions, in 1633. The town was incorporated in 1634. The town
        name, Ipswich, was chosen to honor the merchants of Ipswich, England, who were financial
        supporters of the Massachusetts Bay Company. The First Church in Ipswich was gathered on
        August 5, 1634, and the first meeting house was constructed the same year. Newly arrived
        from England, Nathaniel Ward and Thomas Parker were both settled as the first ministers,
        though Rev. Parker was dismissed after a year in Ipswich to become the pastor in Newbury. In
        1646 the first meeting house was sold and construction on the second meeting house was
        completed in 1647. 1681 a group of parishioners left to form the Second Church in Ipswich,
        also known as the Chebacco Parish, which is now the Congregational Church of Essex.</p>
      <p>In 1699 the third meeting house of the First Church was built on the north green. In 1702,
        a clock was added to the building; this construction was partially funded by the public sale
        of the stone remains of an old fort. In 1714 a group of parishioners left the church to form
        the Third Church in Ipswich, now First Congregational Church in Hamilton. In 1747 a group of
        parishioners left to the South Church in Ipswich after strong disagreements between the two
        settled pastors, Rev. Nathaniel Rogers and Rev. Walley, spilled into the public. In 1749
        another group of parishioners left to form the West Farms Parish, now the Linebrook Church.
        In 1749 the fourth meeting house was constructed to replace the third which was too large
        for the parish following the 1747 and 1749 dismissals. A gilded weathercock was placed atop
        the spire of the fourth meeting house. In 1762 a tower clock was purchased and installed
        into the building. In 1773 the First and South Parishes jointly purchased a burial ground on
        the south side of town</p>
      <p>David T. Kimball was ordained as the fourteenth minister of the First Church in Ipswich on
        October 3, 1806. He had graduated from Harvard in 1803 and studied theology under Rev.
        French in Andover following a year as an instructor at the Phillips' Academy. In 1816, Rev.
        Kimball helped to establish the first Sabbath School of the First Church. He served as the
        minister until he died of pneumonia on February 3, 1860. Construction on the fifth meeting
        house began in 1846 and the new building was dedicated in 1847. The building was one of only
        a few gothic churches constructed out of wood. The weathercock and tower clock of the fourth
        meeting house were incorporated into the fifth.</p>
      <p>After years of declining membership, the South Church voted to reunite with the First
        Church in Ipswich in 1922. Following the merger the new church organization was called the
        First and South Congregational Church. Members from the Linebrook Church rejoined the First
        and South Congregational Church in 1958, though the Linebrook Church continues to exist
        today as an independent church. In 1965 the fifth meeting house was struck by lightning and
        was destroyed in the ensuing fire. The tower clock, thought to be the oldest in-use tower
        clock in the United States in 1965, was destroyed, but the weathercock survived.
        Construction on the sixth meeting house was begun in 1970 and completed in 1971; the weather
        clock was once again incorporated into the new building. At some point between 1961 and 1984
        the First and South Congregational Church reverted to its original name, First Church in
        Ipswich. Now a member of the United Church of Christ, the First Church in Ipswich continues
        to serve the local community today.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_31fbe7593d3edcbe32fe6d2c692a4f29">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains the church and parish records of the First Church in Ipswich. The
        collection documents the history and parish life of the church through meeting minutes,
        reports, financial documents, and vital statistics. In addition, topics such as ministry
        work, pew rights, land discussions, hymns in church, and lists of the sacraments that
        occurred at the different parishes are included within the records. The vital records
        include birth and baptismal records, marriage records, and death records. The collection
        also contains records kept by Rev. David T. Kimball. His papers include both church and
        personal correspondence, manuscript sermons, personal writings, church records, and
        committee reports.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_c021d0786a873135bf5068abfb6c28d4">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged chronologically by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_ecb558fcd678cb1ac5832747ba49a6e4">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and alter, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_15065bcd2a7deb76742ee1407ba87e4f">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>The Congregational Library &amp; Archives has digitized materials from the South Church in
        Ipswich and made <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/nehh/series1/IpswichMASouth5298"
          linktitle="them available to view online" show="new">them available to view
        online</ref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_e4ece15c8098d89b0421e28f481b53e9">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p><emph render="italic">In Gratitude to Almighty God for Three hundred and Fifty Years of
          Service and Witness</emph>. Ipswich: 1984. 17.11.1 I68.7 FirC</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Church correspondence.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85066724" source="lcsh">
        <part>Installation (clergy).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85081512" source="lcsh">
        <part>Marriage records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85088919" source="lcsh">
        <part>Music in churches.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85090572" source="lcsh">
        <part>Necrologies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85100506" source="lcsh">
        <part>Pews and pew rights.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="no2014085949" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Church (Ipswich, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n82058914" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Ipswich (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_f824c420dc88030687db2bd1f5e314c2" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Parish and town records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1724">1724</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1756">1756</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1724-1756</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_b93635c1e5d7999b7cfa7bd2591f4f99">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/IpswichFirst/viewer/Parish20records2C2017241756/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_fada3d64ec1f97bebc622d14832b58d0">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the minutes of the First Parish dating from 1724 to 1755, and also
            contains the minutes of Ipswich town meetings. The minutes document church and town
            happenings and record the votes that took place. The volume chronicles the history and
            development of the town and First Parish of Ipswich. The topics covered include
            salaries, ministry work and assistance, discussions of building a meeting house on the
            South side of the river and its development, and the governance of the parish. The
            volume includes a list of members divided by geographical locations.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_1496b6210f02d8b2182840fbf4f4f567" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church record book</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1709">1709</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1805">1805</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1739-1806</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_fe7931a473b0501256a3489ad0d1284b">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/IpswichFirst/viewer/Church20records2C2017391806/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_d7c2d2018f4a7dea340c7920587df2f8">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume largely contains lists of vital statistics including the birth, baptismal,
            marriage, admission, dismission, and death records of the church from 1739 to 1806. The
            volume also contains hand copied excerpts from other sources pertaining to the founding
            and history of the church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_daef64a36678ceea67cbaa5b43b3484a" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Parish record book</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1757">1757</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1830">1830</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1757-1830</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_6e2497dcff76f7da24b906ad5b0b22e1">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/IpswichFirst/viewer/Parish20records2C2017571830/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_8200dd70b5278cad0294a01b5aba9c58">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the warrants and meeting summaries of the First Parish in Ipswich
            from 1757 to 1830. The meeting summaries cover both the development and governance of
            the First Parish and of the town of Ipswich. Principal topics include payments to
            pastors, records of votes, the burial grounds of the parish, and the role of song in
            church service. Other topics include the pew allocations, including a diagram, division
            of land, and the digging of graves.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_407b495bc7342bcf356232aee09b6e4a" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church and committee records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1807">1807</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1856">1856</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1807-1856, undated</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_972e7f83c9631fbdda8693558132a2b9" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_cbf5af8bbd8b701fdea0f75cd2e74bdb" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_972e7f83c9631fbdda8693558132a2b9">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_d4e86fb7bdaf4de1bae60712064eb808" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Kimball's church correspondence</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1813">1813</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1898">1898</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1813-1898, undated</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_c3187fbc391ad7dcfa80602197599719" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_2e111a3f82e12d2a345688778b1a5098" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_c3187fbc391ad7dcfa80602197599719">27</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_acb863f9346a02724d8b8911a0eb6ab7" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Kimball's personal correspondence</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1829">1829</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1863">1863</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1829-1863, undated</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_b5a38c723008cf632eabae5a18ef26ae" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_5415ee9151e1d195817bf88b4ea095ed" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_b5a38c723008cf632eabae5a18ef26ae">28</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_81a8e51056a251dbc8e554a1ab5427bd" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Kimball's papers and sermons</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1850">1850, undated</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_be14fc58769862aba5bdcf7b85ba9acf" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_49766b7605f05cddf267767cc3b3e662" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_be14fc58769862aba5bdcf7b85ba9acf">29</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
