<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/LancasterMAFirst-5329.xml"
      >LancasterMAFirst-5329</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/LancasterMAFirst-5329.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Lancaster, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1708-1846. </titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-02-12</date>
        <num>RG5329</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-06-03T20:24:10+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Monday June 3, 2019
          at 20:24</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Lancaster, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1708-1846.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5329</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="materialtype">
        <quantity>4</quantity>
        <unittype>Volumes</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" era="ce" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1708">1708</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1846">1846</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" unitdatetype="inclusive">1708-1846</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_88ffff676c0247c107f91375ac0b1624">The town of Lancaster and the First
        Congregational Church in Lancaster were established on November 28, 1653. The first and
        second meeting houses both were destroyed during Native American raids as part of larger
        geopolitical movements. The third meeting house was constructed in 1706 and the fourth in
        1743. During Rev. Timothy Thayer time as minister, the church adopted Unitarian tenants and
        the fifth meeting house, designed by Charles Bulfinch, was constructed. In 1970 the church
        joined the Unitarian Universalist Christian Fellowship. The First Church of Christ,
        Unitarian, in Lancaster continues to serve the local community. This collection contains the
        earliest extant records of the church and includes administrative records, vital records,
        financial records, pew records, and church covenants.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="n92106522" source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Church of Christ (Lancaster, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_2c510fc6b484bacc8d203378d8b02124">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_b3bcccd8d4eea45965357b831b80507b">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_5fc4612108590e04640993076a0e4790">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Lancaster, Mass. First Congregational Church records,
        1708-1846, RG5329. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_f4f9bcc623ad400d3ad7b022fe824a37">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Materials were loaned to the Congregational Library by the First Church of Christ,
        Unitarian, in Lancaster, Massachusetts, in April 2017; Accession 2017-05.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <originalsloc id="aspace_2c311d140d1238b81730a58d4a869135">
      <head>Location of Originals</head>
      <p>The original volumes are held by the First Church of Christ, Unitarian, in Lancaster,
        Massachusetts.</p>
    </originalsloc>
    <accruals id="aspace_24eb2a13a7ef18e57ffb0512c48414d8">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_d1f089858f2bbabf9390311b9e265e2b">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Zachary Bodnar, February 2019, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_6d0d793cbce0b53a1af8727377174752">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The town of Lancaster and the First Congregational Church in Lancaster were established on
        November 28, 1653, with the signing of a civil covenant by the town's first settlers. In
        1654, the town called Joseph Rowlandson, a recent graduate of Harvard, to be the first
        minister. He married Mary White, the daughter of a wealthy settler, in 1656 and was
        officially ordained in 1660. The first meeting house and parsonage were also quickly
        constructed following the installation of Rowlandson. In 1676, as part of King Phillip's
        War, Native Americans attacked the Lancaster garrison. During the attack 12 were killed and
        12 more captured, including Mary Rowlandson, and a number of buildings were burned including
        the meeting house. After 11 weeks, Mary Rowlandson was ransomed back to her family and an
        account of her captivity was published in 1682.</p>
      <p>The second meeting house was constructed in 1684 on the same location as the first. It did
        not survive long as it too was razed during an attack carried out by Native Americans in
        1704 as part of ongoing hostilities between France and England. A third meeting house was
        constructed in 1706 and the first minister to preach in the new building was Rev. John
        Prentice who was installed in 1708. During the First Great Awakening, Rev. Prentice kept the
        Lancaster Church aligned more closely with the traditionalist "Old Lights" than with the
        revivalist "New Lights." The third meeting house was torn down in 1743 and swiftly replaced
        by the fourth meeting house that same year. Rev. Timothy Harrington was the minister of the
        Lancaster church during the American Revolution. In 1777 he was accused of being a Loyalist
        in part because "he was in charity with a professed Roman Catholick." The chargers were
        dropped after Harrington gave an impassioned defense in which he pointed to the principals
        of religious freedom.</p>
      <p>Due to the advanced age and failing health of Rev. Harrington, the town voted to settle a
        junior minister in 1792. In 1793 the town voted to accept Timothy Thayer as the new minister
        and he was ordained in the summer of that year. Rev. Thayer was a member of the Unitarian
        movement and almost immediately began to liberalize the church and make membership into the
        church significantly easier. Due to the move towards Unitarianism, some members of the
        church withdrew and formed the Evangelical Congregational Church of Lancaster in 1839. The
        fifth, and final, meeting house was built in 1816 on the Lancaster green and on January 1,
        1817 a dedication ceremony was held. The meeting house was designed by Charles Bulfinch, one
        of the earliest American-born professional architects, and was entered into the National
        Register of Historic Places and designated a National Historic Landmark in 1970.</p>
      <p>The First Congregational Church and Society were legally incorporated into a single legal
        entity, the First Church of Christ, around 1908. Beginning in 1918, the First Church of
        Christ and Evangelical Church held three union services annually, though the practice was
        discontinued in 1976 at the behest of the Evangelical Church. In 1952, the Rev. Dr.
        Alexander St. Ivanyi was ordained as the minister of the First Church of Christ. Before
        joining the church, Ivanyi had been part of the Hungarian anti-Nazi resistance during World
        War II, was a member of the Hungarian Parliament after the war, as well as the bishop-vicar
        of the Hungarian Unitarian Church. He was forced to leave flee Hungary after the communist
        takeover of the state. In 1970, during Rev. Ivanyi's tenure, the First Church of Christ
        voted to join the Unitarian Universalist Christian Fellowship. Rev. Tom Wintle, who served
        as minister from 1975-1995, also helped create the Lancaster Historical Society. The First
        Church of Christ, Unitarian, in Lancaster continues to serve the local community today.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_19bbc353181e3171813a23641887526c">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains the earliest extant records of the First Church of Christ in
        Lancaster. All earlier records were lost when both the first and second meeting house were
        razed during wars between English colonists and Native Americans. The volumes contain
        valuable records related both to the administration of the church and society as well as the
        vital records of the members of the church. The records include meeting minutes, committee
        reports, financial records, baptismal records, marriage records, necrologies, a pew plan,
        and the various covenants and statements of faith adopted by the church during the
        eighteenth and early nineteenth-centuries.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_7fb529cb3894e1b7d8d39d9432efe07f">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection has been arranged in chronological order by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_37437577ab2d1dbc5da0f81c11820257">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <bibliography id="aspace_fd3c4d6cf7d149de2b670b17f35d23a8">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Wintle, Thomas D. <emph render="italic">A New England Village: The First Church in
          Lancaster</emph>. Lancaster: First Church of Christ in Lancaster, 1985. 17.11.1 L22.72
        FirCC NW 1985</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025649" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church membership.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85066724" source="lcsh">
        <part>Installation (clergy).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85081512" source="lcsh">
        <part>Marriage records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85090572" source="lcsh">
        <part>Necrologies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85100506" source="lcsh">
        <part>Pews and pew rights.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85112383" source="lcsh">
        <part>Registers of births, etc. </part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh94007643" source="lcsh">
        <part>Unitarian controversy.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="n92106522" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Church of Christ (Lancaster, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n82152210" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Lancaster (Mass.) -- Chrch history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_2aac21f4426cb0d193beb84f3e0f06af" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Baptisms</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1708">1708</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1734">1734</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1708-1734</unitdate>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1730">1730</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1734">1734</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1730-1734</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_b7102985815d663ca1e2bdeb575f7b6b">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Lancaster/viewer/Baptisms2C2017081734/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_423bc53256c5b786a0408fee7976cf21">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume, initially created in 1730, is a record of all baptisms performed by Rev.
            John Prentice while minister at the church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_07077889686c68ecbd7c4b14e43481e0" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1708">1708</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1793">1793</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1708-1793</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_704312850e3ab04abd44bf96e327954c">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Lancaster/viewer/Church20records2C2017081793/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <custodhist id="aspace_74135585e3a072c91ff0d7dee909e898">
          <head>Custodial History</head>
          <p>This volume was rebound and interleaved during the 20th century. A note within the
            volume indicates this work was completed in 1848 however the techniques and materials
            used are more consistent with the conservation work of the mid-20th century.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_18451fbf4eaf0331595f7b8a95837b49">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the administrative records of the church as well as the vital
            records of the church's members. The volume contains meeting minutes, records of
            important votes, marriage records, baptismal records, necrologies, lists of admitted
            members and founding documents such as the church covenant. Also included with the
            volume is a bound manuscript pamphlet of the articles of agreement from 1782.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ce73ee2f1f1e7367b11e3133a3affe49" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Parish records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1742">1742</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1794">1794</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1742-1794</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_3671aea501d76b69f25ef0c7154bc5ce">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Lancaster/viewer/Parish20records2C2017421794/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <custodhist id="aspace_e0f2c11188d83900e8c72b6fb06ca9a7">
          <head>Custodial History</head>
          <p>This volume was rebound and underwent major preservation work, likely during the 20th
            century. It appears that a company based in Taunton, Mass. may have done the
            preservation work, though there is no indication what the name of this company may have
            been or when the preservation work was completed.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_3a3b4e6e3f3e2dbc4a3e1c77c063d5f6">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the records of the Lancaster parish and precinct. Included within
            the volume are pew plans, meeting minutes, financial records, and records of votes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_48c6b114fe9c31eb8f6e8c9ef2a32126" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1793">1793</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1846">1846</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1793-1846</unitdate>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_3255a8604a7900c303e0a2d504d6c0cc">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Lancaster/viewer/Church20records2C2017931846/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_3ea1d03585b355e7bc8ee73ae43a48d2">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the administrative records of the church as well as extensive
            records pertaining to the members of the church. Included within the volume are meeting
            minutes, records of votes, membership lists, deacon lists, marriage records, baptismal
            records, ordination records, council and committee reports, and disciplinary
            records.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
