<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/LancasterMAFirst-0109.xml"
      >LancasterMAFirst-0109</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="https://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/default/files/FindingAids/LancasterMAFirst-0109.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Lancaster, Mass. First Church of Christ letter of complaint,
          1779.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Suite 200</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="business">617-523-0470</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline>
            <ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref>
          </addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2024-10-29</date>
        <num>RG0109</num>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS 2019.0.3</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2024-10-29T17:11:28+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v3.2.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday October 29,
          2024 at 17:11</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Lancaster, Mass. First Church of Christ letter of complaint, 1779.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG0109</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <languageset>
          <language langcode="eng">English</language>
          <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
        </languageset>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>1</quantity>
        <unittype>Folder</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <datesingle standarddate="1779">1779</datesingle>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <abstract>The town of Lancaster and the First Congregational Church in Lancaster were
        established on November 28, 1653. The second meeting house was constructed in 1684 and the
        third meeting house was constructed in 1706. The fourth meeting house was constructed in
        1743. Rev. Timothy Thayer was ordained in 1793; a member of the Unitarian movement, he
        liberalized the church during his pastorate resulting in some members withdrawing to form
        the Evangelical Congregational Church in 1839. The fifth meeting house was constructed in
        1816; it was entered into the National Register of Historic Places in 1970. The First Church
        of Christ joined the Unitarian Universalist Christian Fellowship in 1970. The First Church
        of Christ, Unitarian, in Lancaster continues to serve the local community today. This
        collection contains a single signed letter of complaint from three members of the First
        Church of Christ in Lancaster against the minister, Timothy Harrington.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <corpname identifier="n92106522" source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Church of Christ (Lancaster, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict>
      <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict>
      <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite>
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Lancaster, Mass. First Church of Christ letter of
        complaint, 1779, RG0109. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo>
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>No acquisition information is available for this collection.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <altformavail>
      <head>Digital Copies</head>
      <p>Records within this collection were digitized by Liz Shuga. Digital reproductions may be
        accessed online through our <ref
          href="https://congregationallibrary.quartexcollections.com/manuscript-collections/browse-the-first-church-of-christ-records-in-pittsfield-massachusetts"
          >digital archive</ref>.</p>
    </altformavail>
    <processinfo>
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Zachary Bodnar, October 2024, using Describing Archives: A Content
        Standard.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The town of Lancaster and the First Congregational Church in Lancaster were established on
        November 28, 1653, with the signing of a civil covenant by the town's first settlers. In
        1654, the town called Joseph Rowlandson, a recent graduate of Harvard, to be the first
        minister. He married Mary White, the daughter of a wealthy settler, in 1656 and was
        officially ordained in 1660. The first meeting house and parsonage were also quickly
        constructed following the installation of Rowlandson. In 1676, as part of King Phillip's
        War, Native Americans attacked the Lancaster garrison. During the attack 12 were killed and
        12 more captured, including Mary Rowlandson, and a number of buildings were burned including
        the meeting house. After 11 weeks, Mary Rowlandson was ransomed back to her family and an
        account of her captivity was published in 1682.</p>
      <p>The second meeting house was constructed in 1684 on the same location as the first. It did
        not survive long as it too was razed during an attack carried out by Native Americans in
        1704 as part of ongoing hostilities between France and England. A third meeting house was
        constructed in 1706 and the first minister to preach in the new building was Rev. John
        Prentice who was installed in 1708. During the First Great Awakening, Rev. Prentice kept the
        Lancaster Church aligned more closely with the traditionalist "Old Lights" than with the
        revivalist "New Lights." The third meeting house was torn down in 1743 and swiftly replaced
        by the fourth meeting house that same year. Rev. Timothy Harrington was the minister of the
        Lancaster church during the American Revolution. In 1777 he was accused of being a Loyalist
        in part because "he was in charity with a professed Roman Catholick." The chargers were
        dropped after Harrington gave an impassioned defense in which he pointed to the principals
        of religious freedom.</p>
      <p>Due to the advanced age and failing health of Rev. Harrington, the town voted to settle a
        junior minister in 1792. In 1793 the town voted to accept Timothy Thayer as the new minister
        and he was ordained in the summer of that year. Rev. Thayer was a member of the Unitarian
        movement and almost immediately began to liberalize the church and make membership into the
        church significantly easier. Due to the move towards Unitarianism, some members of the
        church withdrew and formed the Evangelical Congregational Church of Lancaster in 1839. The
        fifth, and final, meeting house was built in 1816 on the Lancaster green and on January 1,
        1817 a dedication ceremony was held. The meeting house was designed by Charles Bulfinch, one
        of the earliest American-born professional architects, and was entered into the National
        Register of Historic Places and designated a National Historic Landmark in 1970.</p>
      <p>The First Congregational Church and Society were legally incorporated into a single legal
        entity, the First Church of Christ, around 1908. Beginning in 1918, the First Church of
        Christ and Evangelical Church held three union services annually, though the practice was
        discontinued in 1976 at the behest of the Evangelical Church. In 1952, the Rev. Dr.
        Alexander St. Ivanyi was ordained as the minister of the First Church of Christ. Before
        joining the church, Ivanyi had been part of the Hungarian anti-Nazi resistance during World
        War II, was a member of the Hungarian Parliament after the war, as well as the bishop-vicar
        of the Hungarian Unitarian Church. He was forced to leave flee Hungary after the communist
        takeover of the state. In 1970, during Rev. Ivanyi's tenure, the First Church of Christ
        voted to join the Unitarian Universalist Christian Fellowship. Rev. Tom Wintle, who served
        as minister from 1975-1995, also helped create the Lancaster Historical Society. The First
        Church of Christ, Unitarian, in Lancaster continues to serve the local community today.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains a single signed letter of complaint from three members of the
        First Church of Christ in Lancaster against the minister, Timothy Harrington. In the
        complaint, the three members, William Dunsmoor, Joshua Fletcher, and Hannah Dunsmoor, accuse
        Harrington of being a loyalist and sympathetic to Catholics.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <relatedmaterial>
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>The Congregational Library &amp; Archives digitized materials currently held by the First
        Church of Lancaster, Unitarian Universalist. These materials may be viewed online: <ref
          href="https://congregationallibrary.quartexcollections.com/manuscript-collections/browse-the-first-congregational-church-records-in-lancaster-massachusetts"
          linktitle="view this collection online">Lancaster, Massachusetts. First Congregational
          Church records, 1708-1846.</ref></p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85004364" source="lcsh">
        <part>American loyalists.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025590" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church controversies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Clergy -- Correspondence.</part>
      </subject>
      <geogname identifier="sh85140139" source="lcsh">
        <part>United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.</part>
      </geogname>
      <corpname identifier="n92106522" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Church of Christ (Lancaster, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <persname identifier="n85198586" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Harrington, Timothy, 1715-1795</part>
      </persname>
      <corpname identifier="n82152210" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Lancaster (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter of complaint against Timothy Harrington</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1779">1779</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container
            altrender="http://www.hollingermetaledge.com/modules/store/index.html?dept=566&amp;cat=592&amp;searchname=&amp;searchid=rsb-12&amp;searchtype=C&amp;cart=14743065204309327"
            label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">Small 1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">32</container>
        </did>
      </c>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
