<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/NatickMAFirst-4839.xml"
      >NatickMAFirst-4839</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="https://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/NatickMAFirst4839.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Natick, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1721-1920.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Suite 200</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2022-03-08</date>
        <num>RG4839</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>Portions of this collection are part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital
          historical representations of these portions of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
      <descriptivenote>
        <p>English</p>
      </descriptivenote>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS 2019.0.3</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2022-03-08T15:47:27+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.8.1</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday March 8, 2022
          at 15:47</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Natick, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1721-1920.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG4839</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <languageset>
          <language langcode="eng">English</language>
          <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
        </languageset>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>1.15</quantity>
        <unittype>Cubic Feet</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(1 box, 3 reels)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1721">1721</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1920">1920</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
        >1721-1920</unitdate>
      <abstract>First Congregational Church of Natick, Massachusetts, was established in 1651 by a
        group of English settlers and missionaries under the leadership of Rev. John Elliot. The
        church became home to many local Native Americans, also known as "Praying Indians," and was
        the location of the writing of the "Eliot Bible:" a bible translated into phonetic
        Algonquian. This collection contains records of church covenants, meeting minutes, baptismal
        records, lists of deaths, disciplinary records, ordinations, and membership
        records.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <corpname identifier="nr2005028232" source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Congregational Church (Natick, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict>
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict>
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="https://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite>
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Natick, Mass. First Congregational Church records,
        1721-1920., RG4839. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo>
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>The 1721-1794 church record book was deposited at the Congregational Library &amp; Archives
        by the First Congregational Church of Natick in 2007; no accession number.</p>
      <p>The remaining portion of the collection was deposited at the Congregational Library &amp;
        Archives by the First Congregational Church of Natick in 2016; accession 2016-05. This
        accession was originally provided the identifier RG5313.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <altformavail>
      <head>Digital Copies</head>
      <p>Records within this collection were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
        project. Digital reproductions may be accessed online through our <ref
          href="https://congregationallibrary.quartexcollections.com/manuscript-collections/browse-the-first-congregational-church-records-in-natick-massachusetts"
          linktitle="view digitial reproductions online" show="new">digital archive</ref>.</p>
    </altformavail>
    <accruals>
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo>
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Zachary Bodnar, March 2022, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The First Congregational Church in Natick was established by a group of English settlers
        and missionaries led by Rev. John Eliot in 1651, in what is now old South Natick. The
        settlers cultivated strong relationships with local Indigenous peoples, mainly comprising
        members of the Massachusett tribe, while attempting to convert them to Christianity. To this
        end, Rev. Eliot studied the Algonquin language with the help of the Montaukett interpreter
        Cockenoe, eventually publishing a translation of the Bible in phonetic Algonquin.</p>
      <p>Those who converted were known as "Praying Indians" and became foundational members of the
        First Church in Natick, which was typified by its racially diverse congregation during the
        17th and 18th centuries. There was a sizeable minority of congregants who were identified as
        "Negro" in the earliest church registers, as well as increasing numbers of white members.
        The Native presence persisted despite major fluctuations in their numbers, including those
        resulting from deadly forced removals to Deer Island in 1675, during King Philip's War.</p>
      <p>In 1721 the old meetinghouse was rebuilt and local missionary Rev. Oliver Peabody was
        appointed as minister. During his tenure (1721-1752), he created the first extant records
        for both the church and town. Construction on a third meetinghouse in the same location
        began in 1754.</p>
      <p>By 1749 however, white congregants were lobbying to move the church from South Natick to
        the increasingly segregated Natick Center. These "Center Members" were at odds with the
        largely Indigenous South Natick members who wished to retain the old location. Despite the
        unifying efforts of Rev. Peabody's successor, Rev. Stephen Badger, a fourth meetinghouse was
        eventually built in Natick Center in 1767. In 1798 the congregation officially split,
        largely (although not completely) along racial lines, with both groups retaining the moniker
        of "First Church". Rev. Badger was subsequently dismissed for his refusal to preach at the
        Center church, continuing to reside in South Natick until his death in 1803.</p>
      <p>After the congregational schism, the South Natick division of Natick First fell into
        disrepair, but was revived in 1828 with the incorporation of the South Parish Congregational
        Church and the construction of a new meeting house. The South Parish, which became Unitarian
        in 1870, is now called the Eliot Church and hosts a revived Praying Indian community of
        worship. The "Center" church continued through several physical iterations until the present
        day while retaining the designation of the First Church in Natick. Notable among these was
        the sixth meetinghouse, a costly edifice erected on the same site in 1854, which included a
        bell and fine organ, and played host to several prominent luminaries of the Civil War era.
        This structure however burned down only two decades after its construction, in the great
        Natick fire of 1874. A gothic-style church was erected adjacent to the former site in 1877
        and is still in use. Natick First joined the United Church of Christ shortly after the
        latter organization's foundation in 1957.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains early administrative and financial records for the First
        Congregational Church in Natick. The collection contains administrative records and meeting
        minutes, financial records and ledgers, church membership records, baptismal records,
        marriage records, records of deaths, sermons produced by Benjamin Caryl, church
        correspondence, a list of prohibition supporters, and a history of the Sabbath school in
        Natick.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Materials in this collection have been arranged in chronological order by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech>
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital materials on our digital archive, it is strongly recommended that you use
        the latest available version of Microsoft Edge, Google Chrome, Mozilla Firefox, or Safari
        (Apple).</p>
      <p>A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader
        is available to the public upon request.</p>
    </phystech>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85003480" source="lcsh">
        <part>Algonquin Indians.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025597" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church discipline.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025649" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church membership.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85033612" source="lcsh">
        <part>Covenants (Church polity).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85081512" source="lcsh">
        <part>Marriage records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85090572" source="lcsh">
        <part>Necrologies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85095385" source="lcsh">
        <part>Ordination.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh2008111551" source="lcsh">
        <part>Sermons, American -- Early works to 1800.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85133710" source="lcsh">
        <part>Temperance and religion.</part>
      </subject>
      <persname identifier="n84024575" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Badger, Stephen, 1726-1803</part>
      </persname>
      <corpname identifier="nr2005028232" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Congregational Church (Natick, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n79069737" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Natick (Mass.) -- Church history</part>
      </corpname>
      <persname identifier="n85253116" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Peabody, Oliver, 1698-1752</part>
      </persname>
      <persname identifier="nr2006033289" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Sears, Freeman, 1779-1811</part>
      </persname>
      <corpname identifier="nr2001028763" source="lcnaf">
        <part>South Congregational Church in Natick (Natick, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1721">1721</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1794">1794</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >1721-1794</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="volume">1</container>
          <container label="Microform" localtype="reel">Print Master</container>
          <container label="Microform" localtype="reel">Archival Master</container>
          <container label="Microform" localtype="reel">Service Copy</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the earliest extant records for the town of Natick and of the
            First Church. They begin in 1721, the year in which a second meetinghouse was built and
            in which Rev. Oliver Peabody began his 30 year tenure. It includes lists of members,
            baptisms, deaths, church meetings minutes, and a copy of the church covenant. This
            volume of records includes a list of "those Indians that have Dyed from among us," which
            can be used as an index to track the activities of Native Americans in the church, many
            of whom had anglicized names. Stewardship of the records passed to Rev. Stephen Badger
            in 1752, after Rev. Peabody's death.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <accessrestrict>
          <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
          <p>Of the microfilm reels, only the service copy is available for public use. Master reels
            are restricted and maintained for preservation purposes.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter regarding the building of the third meeting house</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1750">1750</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">12</container>
        </did>
        <phystech>
          <head>Physical Access</head>
          <p>Access to this folder is restricted due to the presence of broken glass. Contact the
            archivist for special permission to view the item. Special gloves must be worn when
            handling this folder.</p>
        </phystech>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter to bereaved parent</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1755">1755</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This single piece of correspondence is both unsigned and unaddressed. Its writer
            expresses sympathy with a bereaved parent whose son was killed in the disastrous defeat
            of General Edward Braddock's forces near Fort Duquesne, in the "Battle of the
            Monongahela" during the French and Indian War. The letter was sent from Boston and dated
            August 4, 1755.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Warrant for meeting about gallery stairs</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1755">1755</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">13</container>
        </did>
        <phystech>
          <head>Physical Access</head>
          <p>Access to this folder is limited due to the presence of glass. Handle with care.</p>
        </phystech>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benjamin Caryl sermons</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1762">1762</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1803">1803</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1762-1803</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"A sermon at the execution of Moses Paul"</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1772">circa 1772</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">3</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail>
          <head>Electronic resource available</head>
          <p>An electronic version of a later edition of this sermon is available through Hathi
            Trust Digital Library: <ref href="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/100310929">A
              Sermon at the execution of Moses Paul</ref></p>
        </altformavail>
        <altformavail>
          <head>Library resource available</head>
          <p>A different edition of this item is available from the Congregational Library &amp;
            Archives: <ref
              href="https://congregationallibrary.softlinkliberty.net:443/liberty/OpacLogin?mode=BASIC&amp;openDetail=true&amp;corporation=CLA&amp;action=search&amp;queryTerm=uuid%3D%2273eec402c0a8e1010055af1500240cc4%22&amp;operator=OR&amp;url=%2Fopac%2Fsearch.do"
              >15.5 5842.1</ref></p>
        </altformavail>
        <phystech>
          <head>Physical Access</head>
          <p>Access to this item is restricted due to the fragility of the object. Please use either
            the edition held by the library or the electronic version on Hathi Trust. Contact the
            archivist for special permission to view this item.</p>
        </phystech>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>A plan of Concert of Prayer circular letter</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1794">1794</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1795">1795</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >1794-1795</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Purchase of town's right to meeting house</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1798">1798</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">14</container>
        </did>
        <phystech>
          <head>Physical Access</head>
          <p>Access to this folder is limited due to the presence of glass. Handle with care.</p>
        </phystech>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1802">1802</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1833">1833</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >1802-1833</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="volume">2</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume dates from shortly after the Church's 1798 schism and comprises the records
            of the "Center" division of Natick First. It includes details of the church's committee
            at the time of formation, articles of faith, the church covenant, financial records,
            member lists, records of baptisms, marriages, deaths, church meeting minutes, and
            correspondence. The death records include detailed mortality information such as age at
            death and cause of death, and occasional demographic details. Correspondence includes a
            letter from Rev. Sears seeking reconciliation with the people of South Natick. A table
            of contents is included at the front of the volume.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ministerial fund records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1802">1802</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1914">1914</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1802-1914</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="volume">3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Freeman Sears letter</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1809">1809</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">15</container>
        </did>
        <phystech>
          <head>Physical Access</head>
          <p>Access to this folder is limited due to the presence of glass. Handle with care.</p>
        </phystech>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1814">1814</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1914">1914</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1814-1914</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="volume">4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"A sermon, delivered at Natick, January 5, 1817, containing a history of said
            town"</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1817">1817</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">5</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail>
          <head>Electronic resource available</head>
          <p>An electronic version of this item is available through the Internet Archives: <ref
              href="https://archive.org/details/sermondelivereda1817moor/page/n7/mode/2up">"A
              Sermon, delivered at Natick, January 5, 1817"</ref></p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This sermon was authored by Martin Moore, but it includes an end note which was
            authored by Freeman Sears, minister at the First Congregational Church of Natick between
            1806 and 1811.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1822">1822</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1862">1862</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >1822-1862</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="volume">5</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume comprises financial ledgers from Natick First's 'Center' church subsequent
            to the congregational split of 1798. The records, kept by various of the church's
            treasurers, detail incoming and outgoing revenue, ministerial salaries, member rates,
            and other miscellaneous expenses.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1833">1833</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1864">1864</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1833-1864</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="volume">6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Daniel Wight papers</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1837">1837</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1919">1919</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1837-1919</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records by Willard Drury</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1856">1856</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1868">1868</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1856-1868</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="volume">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1861">1861</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1866">1866</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1861-1866</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Typewritten excerpt from "The old Indian chronicle"</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1867">1867</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">8</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail>
          <head>Electronic resource available</head>
          <p>A complete copy of the work this item is an excerpt of is available through the Hathi
            Trust Digital Library: <ref href="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/008427689">"The
              old Indian chronicle: being a collection of exceeding rare tracts written and
              published in the time of King Philip's war"</ref></p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This typewritten excerpt contains the text of pages 88 through 96 from "The old Indian
            chronicle", a work by Samuel G. Grace.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1878">1878</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1912">1912</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">1878,
            1900-1912</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">16</container>
        </did>
        <separatedmaterial>
          <head>Separated Materials</head>
          <p>These materials were removed from the volume "Financial records, 1814-1914".</p>
        </separatedmaterial>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Prohibition supporters</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1892">1892</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">9</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Chronological list of members from 1802-1920</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1920">1920</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">10</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This list of members was compiled by Lucy E. Wight.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Early history of the Natick Sabbath School</unittitle>
          <unitdate datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">undated</unitdate>
          <container label="Mixed Materials" localtype="box">1</container>
          <container localtype="folder">11</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
