<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/NewburyMAFirst-0937.xml"
      >NewburyMAFirst-0937</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/NewburyMAFirst-0937.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Newbury, Mass. First Church ecclesiastical council meeting minutes,
          1670.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-05-08</date>
        <num> RG0937</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-05-14T19:19:36+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Tuesday May 14, 2019
          at 19:19</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Newbury, Mass. First Church ecclesiastical council meeting minutes,
        1670.</unittitle>
      <unitid> RG0937</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>1</quantity>
        <unittype>Folder</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <datesingle standarddate="1670">1670.</datesingle>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <datesingle standarddate="1853">1853</datesingle>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <abstract id="aspace_43cbf18c2d3e02bcc540ac0c4d3e0d4b">The town of Newbury, Massachusetts, was
        first settled in 1635. The First Church was gathered in 1635 and construction on the first
        meeting house was completed the same year. In 1743 a group of parishioners left to form the
        First Episcopal Church. Between 1635 and 1806 five meeting houses were constructed. The
        fifth was destroyed in fire in 1868. The sixth, and final, meeting house was constructed in
        1869. The First Church joined the United Church of Christ in 1961 and in 1967 the church was
        renamed to the First Parish Church in Newbury; this church continues to serve the Newbury
        community today. This collection contains a manuscript reproduction, created by Joshua
        Coffin in 1853, of an ecclesiastical council determination called in 1669 and 1670 to advise
        the parish church on questions of governance.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="n91028812" source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Church of Newbury (Newbury, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="n96020966" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Woodbridge, John, 1613-1695</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="source">
        <persname identifier="nr96008996" relator="trc" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Coffin, Joshua, 1792-1864</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_8dcd24fb40baec6191415092368f72ff">
      <head> Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_ca0d10698d947d061687c4da5e2cd1e3">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_f13664b9ff1c0e043a05ed7f70ce538c">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Newbury, Mass. First Church ecclesiastical council meeting
        minutes, 1670, RG0937. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_53874ad87f226ae7f32077f262af2d79">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Presented to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives, August 1853, by Joshua Coffin; no
        accession number.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accruals id="aspace_1d5d24949d0a06c028eb6a5dca4a11c9">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_16e696dab4ad8797595187b293037206">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Originally described by Anderson Boone, September 2014, using DACS Second Edition.
        Reprocessed and redescribed by Zachary Bodnar, May 2019, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_3ea7e00f7ad45879b5928d7b617f209a">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The town of Newbury, Massachusetts, was first settled in 1635. The early European colonists
        settled along the Wessacuçon River, also transcribed as Quascacunquen; the river is now
        known as the Parker River. The First Church in Newbury was formally gathered in 1635 and was
        the twelfth church to be established in the Massachusetts Bay Colony. The first meeting
        house was also constructed in 1635. As the Newbury settlement began to expand north towards
        the Merrimac River the Parish decided to build a more central church. This second meeting
        house was constructed in 1647. In 1661 the third meeting house was constructed across from
        the second to accommodate a larger parish. The fourth meeting house was erected in 1699.</p>
      <p>Three distinct population centers formed in Newbury during the late seventeenth-century. In
        1694 the western portion of Newbury was partitioned into the West Parish and the Second
        Church in Newbury was formed. Another partition took place in 1722 with the creation of the
        Newburyport Parish and gathering of the Third Church in Newbury. Both parishes were
        eventually incorporated as the towns of West Newbury and Newburyport.</p>
      <p>In 1743 a group of parishioners, unhappy with Rev. Christopher Toppan and eager to more
        closely follow the teachings of George Whitefield, withdrew from the First Church. They
        later formed the First Episcopal Church along with a group of parishioners who had also
        withdrawn from the Third Church to better follow George Whitefield's teachings.</p>
      <p>The fifth meeting house was constructed in 1806 and dedicated on September 17, 1806. During
        the nineteenth-century the parish community participated in numerous reform movements. In
        1818 a Sunday school was opened. The following year the Female Reading Society was formed.
        The fifth meeting house was destroyed in a fire on January 26, 1868. Construction on the
        sixth, and final, meeting house was completed in 1869.</p>
      <p>In 1961 the church voted to join the United Church of Christ. In 1967 the parish and church
        organizations were merged and the name of the church was changed to First Parish Church of
        Newbury. The First Parish Church continues to serve the Newbury community today.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_c0d58e63d344d61fae900bcaa97ee759">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains a manuscript reproduction of an ecclesiastical council declaration
        called in 1669 and 1670. The original was made in the hand of Rev. John Woodbridge and the
        copy was produced by Joshua Coffin in 1853. The council was called to advise the Newbury
        church on a proposal to change their church governance from a Council of Elders to a more
        democratic system. The response of the council was overwhelmingly negative; they claimed
        that such a process was against the Congregational way and promoted popery. Despite this, by
        1683, Newbury First had no ruling elders.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <phystech id="aspace_e99d5b7a8c510c5f77cff1e11cfa46ad">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_cdffe5bf68a10e8c94aa51b8ada21070">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>The records of the First Parish Church in Newbury, Massachusetts, are housed at the The
        Phillips Library at the Peabody Essex Museum and are open and available for research use. In
        addition, some of these records have been digitized as part of the New England's Hidden
        Histories project and digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/nehh/series1/NewburyMAFirst0937"
          linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_4fa64dfe45c9fef6e0118aa558ad026b">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>The 350th Committee. <emph render="italic">First Parish Church: 350th Anniversary
          All-Church Banquet, June 23, 1985</emph>. Newbury: 1985. 17.11.1 N45.2 FirCN</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85025590" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church controversies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <persname identifier="nr96008996" relator="trc" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Coffin, Joshua, 1792-1864</part>
      </persname>
      <corpname identifier="n91028812" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Church of Newbury (Newbury, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n81117689" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Newbury (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_0e5488935b7664ae80dd56d76ab245aa" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Council minutes</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1670">1670</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1853">1853</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_2c4878c77420182ba97c308051b30b2b" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_966698940731b663271d6e12079503fa" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_2c4878c77420182ba97c308051b30b2b">10</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_da3b978f22da9a4755569ac535719df3">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These ecclesiastical council meeting records were digitized as part of the New
            England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Newbury/viewer/Ecclesiastical20council20meeting20minutes2C2016691670/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
