<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/RowleyMAFirst-4836.xml"
      >RowleyMAFirst-4836</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/RowleyMAFirst-4863.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Rowley, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1664-1941.</titleproper>
        <author>Jules Thomson</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-10-04</date>
        <num>RG4836</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>Portions of this collection are part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital
          historical representations of these portions of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition (DACS)</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-10-04T18:36:19+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Friday October 4,
          2019 at 18:36</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Rowley, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1664-1941.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG4836</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>0.67</quantity>
        <unittype>Cubic Feet</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(2 boxes, 7 reels)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1664">1664</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1941">1941</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1664-1941</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_e5785c724374166e340a7488f97b9d93">The First Church of Rowley, Mass. was
        founded in 1639 by Rev. Ezekiel Rogers and his followers, who had departed their Anglican
        church in Rowley, Yorkshire, UK in protest over lax Sabbath laws. Rev. Rogers was a notable
        Puritan whose conservative zeal influenced the governance of the Massachusetts Bay Colony.
        The church continues to serve the community today as a member of the United Church of
        Christ. This collection contains the earliest church, parish, and financial records
        beginning in 1664, and microfilmed versions of the records also include more recent
        administrative records.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="n2002037865" source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Church (Rowley, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="nr2001012471" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Phillips, Samuel, 1725-1796</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="n85145346" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Jewett, Jedidiah, 1705-1774</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_7c60e31dda4ace90e09741ea7b8638f1">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_3882dcabf47854e59cd37eb1a63cacbc">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_85402a7d5bee2b5637d3c91b2314c27a">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Rowley, Mass. First Church records, 1664-1835, RG4836. The
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_64502c94dd8b7e4b9681bd18e6bbec66">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Materials were permanently loaned to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives by the First
        Congregational Church, Rowley (UCC) in August 2011. There is no accession number for this
        collection.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accruals id="aspace_4c80c67119002714eab4b0737dbead7a">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <custodhist id="aspace_afc2b60d2c3d752a7e686c91aca69c8e">
      <head>Custodial History</head>
      <p>The earliest volume of church records, 1664-1784 (also known as the "Phillips Diary") was
        assumed lost by the church during the later 20th century, but was recovered in 2007 from a
        deposit box in the Rowley branch of the First National Bank of Ipswich. The volume was
        extensively conserved by the Northeast Document Conservation Center in 2010 and microfilmed
        shortly afterwards.</p>
      <p>Microfilm records, 1664-1784 were created in 2010 from the physical volume of church
        records 1664-1748 (also known as the "Phillips Diary"). The microfilm was imaged and
        produced by the Northeast Document Conservation Center.</p>
      <p>Microfilm records, 1664-1941 were copied in 2007 from the original negatives loaned by the
        church, which have no known provenance.</p>
      <p>Microfilm records, 1730-1835 were imaged and produced in 2008 by the Northeast Document
        Conservation Center.</p>
    </custodhist>
    <processinfo id="aspace_a7f5ca9ce7dc93ac9f77b74c74b3d49f">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed and described by Jules Thomson, October 2019, using DACS Second edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_309e76e8145f13f93e9154768ad964be">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The original founders of the church and town of Rowley, Mass. came from the town of the
        same name in the East Riding of Yorkshire, UK. Rev. Ezekiel Rogers, the leader of the
        settlers, was the assistant pastor at St. Peter's Church of England in Rowley, and a staunch
        supporter of puritanical observance of the Sabbath. He found himself at odds with the
        Anglican authorities, who issued a decree allowing the playing of sports on Sundays. He and
        at least 21 families separated themselves in protest and left for the New World on the ship
        John, settling in the area in 1638. The land for the settlement was purchased for 800 pounds
        from Newbury and Ipswich, and the town was officially incorporated on September 4, 1639. The
        settlers brought with them a high level of expertise in the manufacture of cotton, hemp and
        flax cloth, and constructed the first fulling mill in America.</p>
      <p>The first meeting house was erected at the intersection of Central Street (then Holmes
        Street) and Wethersfield Street, and dedicated on December 3, 1639. This building was used
        for Sunday services and Lecture Days (midweek services) in addition to secular town
        business.</p>
      <p>Rev. Rogers became a persuasive leader in the development of the puritanical government of
        the Court of Massachusetts Bay Colony. He was one of four ministers from Essex County chosen
        to rule on questions of church and colonial law, and the first recorded preacher at a
        council of Congregational Churches in New England. Less puritanical members were offended by
        his religious zeal; among his strong beliefs was that private members should not make
        speeches in church assemblies.</p>
      <p>Rev. Rogers was married three times; his first two wives, Joan Hartopp and Joan Nelson,
        both died in childbirth along with the child. He married the widow Mary Barker in July of
        1651. On the night of the marriage, Rev. Roger's home, furnishings, library, and church
        records were destroyed by a fire, popularly believed to be arson by a woman whom Rev. Rogers
        had refused to marry. Shortly after the fire he fell from his horse and broke his right arm,
        which became permanently useless. He died in 1660 and was buried in the Rowley Cemetery.</p>
      <p>The Rev. Samuel Phillips (Harvard College, 1650) was settled in June, 1651, as a teacher on
        a salary varying from £50 to £90 per annum. When Rev. Rogers's health began to seriously
        decline, Mr. Phillips largely took over the ministry despite his lay status, and the town
        selectmen ordered that £5 should be paid to him for this service. This led to a protracted
        18-year dispute with Rev. Rogers's widow, who claimed that the funds had been appropriated
        illegally. The case was decided in her favor by the Ipswich court, but was later overruled
        by the Massachusetts General Court in 1679.</p>
      <p>In 1665, Samuel Shepard (Harvard College, 1658) was ordained pastor of the church, Mr.
        Phillips still acting as teacher. After Rev. Shepard's death in 1668, Mr. Phillips was
        finally ordained as pastor and continued in the role until his death in 1696.</p>
      <p>In 1695 the town voted to build a new meeting house, and construction was completed in May
        of 1697. All notified persons were required to assist with the construction or be fined
        three shillings per day. This second building measured 50x40 feet and included a gallery and
        glass windows transferred from the previous meeting house. It also featured benches which
        were partitioned into men and women's seating areas.</p>
      <p>Construction began on a third meeting house in 1747, which measured 60x42 feet with a
        steeple on the north side and porch on the south. The interior featured a large pulpit and
        sounding board and a broad aisle with galleries to the front and sides. In August of 1777
        the meeting house was damaged by a lightning strike. Repairs were withheld until 1781, after
        the end of the Revolutionary War, using funds acquired from the auctioning off of space for
        additional pews.</p>
      <p>In 1841 it was voted to build a fourth meeting house, and a change in location to the
        corner of Hammond and Main Streets was proposed. The congregation became divided over the
        issue, with parishioners on the south side of the Ox Pasture Brook favoring the move and
        those to the north side opposed to it. A vote was held and decided by a single vote, with 24
        members in favor of re-location and 23 against. This resulted in a number of dissatisfied
        parishioners splitting off from the Rowley church and attending service in the neighboring
        Byfield parish.</p>
      <p>The First Congregational Church of Rowley received official incorporation in 1889, and
        continues to serve the community today as a member of the United Church of Christ.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_2ef35e6f6e832e4becd71d1b08e1a4ef">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection documents the administrative history of the church and the religious life
        of its members. It contains the earliest church, parish, and financial records beginning in
        1664, as well as a "double" volume containing both personal notes of the Rev. Jedidiah
        Jewett and a listing of marriages. Additionally, there are microfilmed records replicating
        most of the physical volumes, and also including more recent administrative records dating
        after the church's incorporation in 1889.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_783d2a324b5f6658a2bd82beb22108ac">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Materials have been arranged in chronological order by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech id="aspace_7ebdcd47af500880cb99cecc23dfd079">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader
        is available to the public upon request.</p>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <bibliography id="aspace_ccb391b54cfe64f9cda3f9455326a295">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>"History." The Congregational Church of Rowley. Accessed October 3, 2019. <ref
          href="http://www.firstchurchrowley.org/about/who-we-are/history-2/"
          >http://www.firstchurchrowley.org/about/who-we-are/history-2/</ref></p>
      <p>Wheatland, Henry. <emph render="italic">Standard History of Essex County, Massachusetts:
          Embracing a History of the County from Its 1. Settlement to the Present Time, with a
          History and Description of Its Towns and Cities. (By Cyrus M Tracy Henry
          Wheatland).</emph> Boston: Jewett, 1878.</p>
      <p>Davis, Emerson. <emph render="italic">Biographical Sketches of the Congregational Pastors
          of New England: Volume IV</emph>, n.d.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh89002058" source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025597" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church discipline.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025649" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church membership.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85033612" source="lcsh">
        <part>Covenants (Church polity).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85066724" source="lcsh">
        <part>Installation (clergy).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85078354" source="lcsh">
        <part>Lord's Supper.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85095385" source="lcsh">
        <part>Ordination.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="n2002037865" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Church (Rowley, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n2010063462" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Rowley (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_9b163cb4790bd8069a44ac8deea7b2ad" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1664">1664</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1784">1784</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1664-1784</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_4015d392720942a18542ae23987811dd" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">2</container>
          <container id="aspace_0a0aa793de0390ad5fb3d8373442119b" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_4015d392720942a18542ae23987811dd">1</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_45ecdbb5a9316ad58859f0e7848521af">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Rowley/viewer/Phillips20Diary2C2016641784/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_afeb6db7925774b339ba58e8b071c15a">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This bound volume, also known as "The Phillips Diary", contains early records of both
            the church and the community in Rowley, including meeting minutes, church covenants,
            baptisms, marriages, and death lists recorded by Rev. Samuel Phillips. Further records
            include disciplinary matters, ecclesiastical councils, and other details of
            seventeenth-century life in the area.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_37d7e061bb1112d0f298a525cc96de45" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Microfilm records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="bulk">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1664">1664</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1784">1784</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="bulk">1664-1784</unitdate>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" certainty="approximate" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >2010</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_2c9aec6a1e1e4fe68bd09bf90723e4aa" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >Service Copy</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_dcc09dc70c32ae7699014645829ad1b7">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This microfilm contains photographic copies of the Church records, 1664-1784, also
            known as the "Phillips Diary". This document is housed, as part of this collection, at
            the CLA.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_9198b62f65ec3cb779dfc9e1d15722d3" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Microfilm records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="bulk">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1664">1664</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1941">1941</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="bulk">1664-1941</unitdate>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="2007">2007</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_7a23dab2d60a4b5ff8eed994e9a2658d" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_f3f8d89c80a5ef6850e64280313e14ef" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >2</container>
          <container id="aspace_e7a303b955642012a7f3d9cb0864b4b9" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >3</container>
        </did>
        <accessrestrict id="aspace_fc6ea177265a08d8739abf46e843dc72">
          <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
          <p>Only the service copy is available for library use. The archival master and print
            master copies are restricted for preservation purposes.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_9ac08f4534dfd56e48af9961a14e213c">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This microfilm contains photographic copies of church records, parish records,
            treasurer's books, vital records, and ministerial records, some of the physical versions
            of which are part of this collection. A detailed listing of these follows:</p>
          <list listtype="deflist">
            <head>Reel 1</head>
            <defitem>
              <label>CR I</label>
              <item>Church Records (also known as the "Phillips Diary"), 1664-1784</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>CR II</label>
              <item>Church Records, 1742-1782</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>CR III</label>
              <item>Church Records, 1782-1835</item>
            </defitem>
          </list>
          <list listtype="deflist">
            <head>Reel 2</head>
            <defitem>
              <label>CR IV</label>
              <item>Vital Statistics and list of ministers, 1840-1870</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>CR V</label>
              <item>Meetings, 1870-1920</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>C Misc.</label>
              <item>Jedidiah Jewett's Extract Book, 1730-1783</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>C Misc.</label>
              <item>Church records pre-incorporation and Church Corporation Records,
                1889-1941</item>
            </defitem>
          </list>
          <list listtype="deflist">
            <head>Reel 3</head>
            <defitem>
              <label>PR I</label>
              <item>Parish Records, 1733-1782</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>PR II</label>
              <item>Parish Records, 1781-1882</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>PR III</label>
              <item>Parish Records, 1822-1870</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>PT I</label>
              <item>Parish Treasurer, 1743-1832</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>PT II</label>
              <item>Parish Treasurer, 1833-1862</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>PR IV</label>
              <item>Parish Records, 1892-1903</item>
            </defitem>
          </list>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_f841a4f48e66b51d7a36a6b89be8e22d" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church and parish records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1728">1728</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1782">1782</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1728-1782</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_6ac539d56957faa7a4e5440e4fe80f70" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_877aa48ff89b3fb64a757871a39d34b1" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_6ac539d56957faa7a4e5440e4fe80f70">1</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_f868552ea4a3e4593250cc359835acc3">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Rowley/viewer/Church20Records2C201742178220and20Parish20Records2C2017281763/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_c6fdacb62a8ab9161b8b089f7d2312cc">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume largely consists of church meeting minutes concerning the selection of new
            ministers – Jedidiah Jewett in 1728 and Jonathan Allin in 1780 – and records regarding
            their salaries.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_0ffa35cbfa592d42e0592e73fee77b2e" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Jedidiah Jewett extract and marriage book</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1730">1730</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1783">1783</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1730-1783</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_5370859f0cf383390fa799b3cce629e0" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_809893262bb940f9bc11114b5de333e2" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_5370859f0cf383390fa799b3cce629e0">2</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_3d37db0db1480ed4c3dc3a2d37c0ca77">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Rowley/viewer/J20Jewett20Extract20and20Marriage20Book2C2017301783/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_e774a4e339780c87500d93ba427d87f7">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This bound book contains two volumes, each starting at opposite covers and using the
            righthand pages in its respective orientation. The "extract" portion contains Rev.
            Jedidiah Jewett's transcribed excerpts from philosophical and historical texts and local
            newspapers. The "marriage book" records marriages performed in the church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_9f2dda4684886b8aa64d0a20e2f3794c" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Microfilm records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1730">1730</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1835">1835</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1730-1835</unitdate>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="2008">2008</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_9271dac47c69ad9eb37fbf6e1dd07a85" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >Service Copy</container>
          <container id="aspace_be690c58dad6136c176f3f61c5b94fc0" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >Archival Master</container>
          <container id="aspace_af6dd2fb45827bdfaafe48c3a1445748" label="Microform" localtype="reel"
            >Print Master</container>
        </did>
        <accessrestrict id="aspace_2fb8932f0620157b0e65584af9e7dab6">
          <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
          <p>Only the service copy is available for library use. The archival master and print
            master copies are restricted for preservation purposes.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_d1ca8dd331981ad2d350fee69afa3055">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This microfilm contains photographic copies of Rev. Jedidiah Jewett's personal
            notebook, parish records, church records, and a treasurer's book, all of the physical
            versions of which are a part of this collection. A detailed listing of these
            follows:</p>
          <list listtype="deflist">
            <head>Reel 1</head>
            <defitem>
              <label>Section 1: C Misc.</label>
              <item>Jewett's Extract Book, 1730-1783</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>Section 2: PR I</label>
              <item>Parish Records, 1733-1782</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>Section 3: PR II </label>
              <item>Parish Records, 1781-1882</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>Section 4: CR-PR </label>
              <item>Church Records and Parish Records, 1742-1782 and 1728-1763</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>Section 5: CR III </label>
              <item>Church Records, 1782-1835</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
              <label>Section 6: PT I</label>
              <item>Parish Treasurer, 1743-1832</item>
            </defitem>
          </list>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_3e3e0d4303ae2fe3bf51ca6dd4bc2ac5" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Parish records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1733">1733</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1782">1782</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1733-1782</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_778b526911493bcac0cb5849ae5ffdd9" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_65522cc551b0525ba1a08adfd08e9c71" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_778b526911493bcac0cb5849ae5ffdd9">3</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_87d1e55db2763e6058a95cceaf2e51a6">
          <head>Existence and Location of Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Rowley/viewer/Parish20Records2C2017331782/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_268a2634b771bbad78e7f4901226cca3">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains financial and administrative records, including church meeting
            minutes and financial information pertaining to officers' salaries and other
            expenditures.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_c427745c618376795e1cb3dd015150b7" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1743">1743</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1832">1832</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1743-1832</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_1b328bce9d9f320a6e9118ce11b4597f" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_988b8c83f328b57a4c83fb81c68c1f01" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_1b328bce9d9f320a6e9118ce11b4597f">4</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_416d4156788209e9f9f1b068a3343443">
          <head>Existence and Location of Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Rowley/viewer/Parish20treasurer2C2017431832/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_51c3adcc25656c3d94a25aa08711dcd2">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This bound volume of records was kept by the church treasurers, and includes salary
            records for ministers and other church officers, pew rents, taxes, and other incomes and
            expenses relating to the running of the church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_4754ef73c24e3f602f9795a196e0ed2f" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Parish records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1781">1781</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1822">1822</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1781-1822</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_ee0459c18ba842f92807c03efb70ab5a" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_58e96492317af0f2c76d792387d5c3ce" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_ee0459c18ba842f92807c03efb70ab5a">5</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_7da1be903c8ce72505b592355244c8e7">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Rowley/viewer/Parish20Records2C2017811822/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_608e0448b6bbdf00763c51595beb0a38">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains financial and administrative records, including church meeting
            minutes and financial information pertaining to officers' salaries and other
            expenditures. It also includes the results of an ecclesiastical council convened to
            resolve a dispute within the church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_5f91cba3f06b778f7a9065a96a42e2b9" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1782">1782</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1835">1835</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1782-1835</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_10aa33f47e30bd751d07a314319db9f9" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">1</container>
          <container id="aspace_ec64d5b0b3d1213f886bb5652dab529a" localtype="volume"
            parent="aspace_10aa33f47e30bd751d07a314319db9f9">6</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_817b55a6b50143194c913e5412247a5e">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Rowley/viewer/Church20Records2C2017821835/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_5ccc5d95924370652c1ad905485a12a4">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>These records are primarily vital statistics and membership records, including
            admissions, dismissions, baptisms, marriages, and deaths. They also contain a number of
            disciplinary cases, mostly for intemperance or poor attendance on the Sabbath.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
