<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/SalemMASouth-5128.xml"
      >SalemMASouth-5128</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/SalemMASouth-5128.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Salem, Mass. South Church records, 1774-1805.</titleproper>
        <author>Jules Thomson</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-09-11</date>
        <num>RG5128</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-09-11T20:00:54+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Wednesday September
          11, 2019 at 20:00</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Salem, Mass. South Church records, 1774-1805.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5128</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>1</quantity>
        <unittype>Volume</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1744">1744</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1805">1805</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1744-1805</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_215318d6850d52eb763b34f53af1425e">The South Church in Salem,
        Massachusetts, was formally founded in 1775 by parishioners separating from the Tabernacle
        Church of Salem after a disagreement with the pastor, Rev. Nathaniel Whitaker. This society
        was initially known as the Third Church, but changed its name to South Church in 1805. The
        church re-merged with the Tabernacle Church in 1924. Records consist of a bound volume of
        the earliest records of the Third Church of Salem, later known as the South Church, and
        includes meeting minutes, votes, pew assignments, and pew tax records.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="n85387652" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Hopkins, Daniel, 1734-1814</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="nr98035144" source="lcnaf">
          <part>South Church (Salem, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname identifier="n85313488" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Third Church (Salem, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_085d39a0dcbce02ae3f88ddc0425ccfe">
      <head> Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_bc425d3d938546fe2980ee04abc66943">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_d49739bce99bb86b7fe2d4c9c8b51c4c">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Salem, Mass. South Church records, 1774-1805, RG5128. The
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_0254184f1e2d76fa5b4d221ce104ed25">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Materials were gifted to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives by the Tabernacle Church
        in November 2013; 2013-25.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accruals id="aspace_ffecc6a33c5307d3935e7ac715ac2a6f">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_5e048022d433ab571ac3ec9568dbab4e">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed and described by Jules Thomson, August 2019, using DACS Second edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_28009c8da782c4f7685a348a945939ec">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>The South Church in Salem, Massachusetts, was formally founded in 1775 by parishioners
        separating from the Tabernacle Church of Salem after a disagreement with the pastor, Rev.
        Nathaniel Whitaker. Rev. Whitaker, an initially popular revolutionary and evangelist, was
        increasingly guiding the Tabernacle toward Presbyterian affiliation. By the end of the year
        1773, there was a group within the Tabernacle expressing "their earnest desire that the
        church be allowed to return and rest upon the stable basis of pure and unmixed
        Congregationalism." Rev. Whitaker attempted to resolve this conflict by securing the
        signatures of twenty members to require the decision of a presbytery, which, meeting in
        September of 1774, suggested that a joint council of both Congregational and Presbyterian
        advisers decide the matter. The congregation of the Tabernacle church, for unknown reasons,
        objected to this, and therefore in October of 1774 the aggrieved brethren withdrew their
        names from enrollment and formed a new society, totaling 14 members. This society was
        initially known as the Third Church, but changed its name to South Church in 1805 when the
        Proprietors of the New South Meeting House received incorporation.</p>
      <p>The church settled their first pastor, Rev. Daniel Hopkins (1734-1814), in 1775 and
        ordained him in November of 1778. Rev. Hopkins was a native of Waterbury, Connecticut who
        had graduated from Yale in 1758. He served as a delegate to the Third Provincial Congress of
        Massachusetts in 1775, shortly after the outbreak of the American Revolution, and he later
        served on the Governor's Council from 1776 to 1778. He remained with the church until his
        death in 1814. However, he suffered from poor health and in April 1805 a second pastor was
        appointed to assist him, Rev. Brown Emerson (1778-1872), who had graduated from Dartmouth
        three years earlier. In 1806, Rev. Emerson married Rev. Hopkins' daughter Mary, and went on
        to serve the church for many years after Rev. Hopkins' death. Like Hopkins, he was also
        assisted by a younger pastor in his later years, but he remained with the church for a total
        of nearly 70 years, until his death in 1872 at the age of 94.</p>
      <p>For the first 30 years of its existence, the separatist congregation had met in a building
        on Cambridge Street, but in 1804 construction began on a new meeting house at the corner of
        Cambridge and Chestnut Streets. This Federal-style building was designed by prominent local
        architect Samuel McIntire, and included pilasters on the front of the building, a Palladian
        window, a pediment above the front entrance, and an ornate, multi-stage steeple that rose
        from the top of the pediment. The first steeple was destroyed in an apparent hurricane on
        September 11, 1804.</p>
      <p>This building was later destroyed by a fire in 1903 and replaced with a stone, Gothic-style
        church bearing little resemblance to its predecessor. This new building was only used by the
        South Church for 20 years, after which it re-merged with the Tabernacle Church, in 1924. As
        of 2019, this organization continues to serve the Salem community as the Tabernacle
        Congregational Church, UCC.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_15cac3087de9cab51463643c014ef094">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>These records consist of a bound volume of the earliest records of the Third Church of
        Salem, later known as the South Church, and includes meeting minutes, votes, pew
        assignments, and pew tax records.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <phystech id="aspace_1bfc9e0dd003b8ef193c97264fd9caa2">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_8a81d72b01bcee2ba72e4ed0cb396060">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>The Congregational Library &amp; Archives has digitized materials from the South Church in
        Salem and made <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/nehh/series1/SalemMASouth5128"
          linktitle="them available to view online" show="new">them available to view
        online</ref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_ea7c652b0cdc7fbf4713591eed5b4b85">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>"South Church, Salem, Mass." Lost New England, February 5, 2019.
        http://lostnewengland.com/2019/02/south-church-salem-mass/.</p>
      <p>Piemonte, Catherine, ed., <emph render="italic">Salem's Church with the Lighted
          Steeple</emph>. Salem, 2008. 17.11.1 S24.6 TABC P2008 C.1</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85100506" source="lcsh">
        <part>Pews and pew rights.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="nr98035144" source="lcnaf">
        <part>South Church (Salem, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n85313487" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Tabernacle Church (Salem, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n85313488" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Third Church (Salem, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_68cc37721aa03c0617b30948d928cdab" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records, 1774-1805</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1774">1774</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1805">1805</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">1774-1805</unitdate>
          <container id="aspace_874d25248d2b64f3aec463de3775bac5" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_ac13497a1ec35c8e0239123fe695056e" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_874d25248d2b64f3aec463de3775bac5">30</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent id="aspace_11f449e2e0545bb718994b97548c4923">
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume contains the earliest records of South Church in Salem, Massachusetts. It
            includes records of meeting minutes and votes, pew assignments, and pew tax records.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <altformavail id="aspace_3f01028a00251729e3c7b7fc333f7c12">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/SalemSouth/viewer/Church20records2C2017741805/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
