<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/SheffieldMAHousatonic-4866.xml"
      >SheffieldMAHousatonic-4866</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/SheffieldMAHousatonic-4866.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Sheffield, Mass. Second North Housatonic Parish of Sheffield covenant and
          confession of faith, 1743.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-06-24</date>
        <num>RG4866</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-06-24T20:19:21+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Monday June 24, 2019
          at 20:19</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Sheffield, Mass. Second North Housatonic Parish of Sheffield covenant and
        confession of faith, 1743.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG4866</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>1</quantity>
        <unittype>Folder</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <datesingle standarddate="1743">1743</datesingle>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <abstract id="aspace_def7b26f77cc5758212270d80958c724">In 1743 the Second North Housatonic
        Parish of Sheffield was gathered with Rev. Samuel Hopkins as the first minister. The first
        meeting house was completed by 1743. In 1761 the North Parish of Sheffield was incorporated
        as the town of Great Barrington and the church was renamed to the First Congregational
        Church of Great Barrington. In 1769 Rev. Hopkins was dismissed after both financial and
        religious difficulties between him and the parish community. The second meeting house was
        constructed in 1813 and the third in 1860. In 1882 the church was destroyed by fire and the
        fourth, and final, meeting house was constructed on the third's foundation. In 1955 the
        church joined the United Church of Christ. The First Congregational Church continues to
        serve the Great Barrington community today. This collection contains the original manuscript
        covenant and confession of faith.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <persname identifier="n85024934" source="lcnaf">
          <part>Hopkins, Samuel, 1721-1803</part>
        </persname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname rules="rda" source="local">
          <part>Second North Housatonic Parish of Sheffield (Sheffield, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_5fa739f6238adcf2b10fa6f413e96ee9">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_f3e6f6d979646a535e4250716af529ec">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_8c6de2b63dfd073031b182e279ccc332">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Sheffield, Mass. Second North Housatonic Parish of
        Sheffield covenant and confession of faith, 1743, RG4866. The Congregational Library &amp;
        Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_808170c87433b7de9f238608af3271e2">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Gifted to the Congregational Library &amp; Archives, 1960, by the First Congregational
        Church in Great Barrington, Massachusetts; no accession number.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accruals id="aspace_5864077bc1aa2e5f968c9ac5368d2244">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_e0a1e01bbe990fa24d89526d654b672f">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Zachary Bodnar, June 2019, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_e1aa124fe803b9bb4079042e13db0cfc">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>In 1742 the pioneer inhabitants of the northern part of Sheffield, Massachusetts,
        petitioned the General Assembly for incorporation. While this request was denied by the
        General Assembly, the Housatonic Village was recognized as the North Parish of Sheffield.
        Construction on the first meeting house began in the spring of 1742 and was completed by
        1743. Samuel Hopkins, a recent graduate of Yale and protégé of Rev. Johnathan Edwards, was
        called to become the first settled minister for the Housatonic Village. Hopkins evidently
        had some reservations about the call due to his scholarly nature, but ultimately accepted.
        He was ordained on December 28, 1743 and the church was officially gathered as the Second
        North Housatonic Parish of Sheffield; at the time only five others were given full
        membership into the church. In 1761 the North Parish was incorporated as the town of Great
        Barrington and the church was renamed to the First Congregational Church of Great
        Barrington.</p>
      <p>Rev. Samuel Hopkins' pastorate was largely defined by both financial and religious
        difficulties. The parish had difficulty meeting Rev. Hopkins' already low salary and it
        seems that he was often underpaid during the whole of his pastorate. Some of his financial
        difficulties were exacerbated by his strict theological beliefs and rejection of the
        Half-Way Covenant which allowed the children of baptized non-members to have their children
        baptized in the church. The Housatonic Village included a sizable population of settlers
        with Dutch backgrounds who largely did not agree with strict Congregational polity. Around
        1760, a number of Dutch inhabitants were confined in public stocks for their failure to
        attend public worship. At around the same time upwards of 60 children had been refused the
        rite of baptism since their parents were not full members of the church. These two events
        caused significant tension between Rev. Hopkins and the parish community. In 1763 an
        Episcopal church was gathered and its members no longer paid the town tax which supported
        Rev. Hopkins. By 1769, the parish refused to appropriate funds for Rev. Hopkins' continued
        ministry and he was subsequently dismissed as the minister by an Ecclesiastical Council.</p>
      <p>The First Congregational Church did not have another settled minister until May 4, 1787
        when Rev. Isaac Foster was settled as the second minister of the church. He was dismissed in
        1790 after the town could not, once again, raise the funds necessary to cover his salary. In
        1791 the town was legally divided into two religious societies, one Congregational and the
        other Episcopal; practically, this legislative change simply formalized the system of ones
        taxes only going to support the minister at the church they belonged to. The church again
        remained without a settled minister until September 24, 1806, when Elijah Wheeler was
        ordained; at the time there were only 21 church members.</p>
      <p>Rev. Wheeler did much to expand church membership during his tenure, even at times going
        against Congregational precepts to welcome new members, especially the infirm. He also
        oversaw the construction of the second meeting house; the first meeting house was apparently
        in serious neglect by the time he was installed as the minister. On December 28, 1813 the
        second meeting house, designed by Captain John Ford, was dedicated. Rev. Wheeler served
        until 1823 when he was replaced by Rev. Sylvester Burt on account of Wheeler's declining
        health. In 1826 the church joined the Massachusetts Sunday School Union and appropriated
        funds to create a Sabbath School library. The church also participated in a number of other
        social initiatives during the first half of the nineteenth-century such as providing
        financial support to the American Board of Foreign Missions and passing a temperance
        resolution in 1840.</p>
      <p>In 1859 construction on the third meetinghouse was begun with the removal of the second
        meetinghouse's steeple to be reused in the new building. The third meeting house, which was
        Romanesque in design, was completed in 1860. In 1879 a chapel was adjoined to the church
        building. Both were destroyed to a fire on March 4, 1882. The lower walls and foundation of
        the third meeting house were reused in the construction of the fourth, and final, meeting
        house. This structure, designed by William C. Brocklesby, was entered into the National
        Register of Historic Places in 1992.</p>
      <p>In 1955 the First Congregational Church of Great Barrington joined the United Church of
        Christ. The church remains active today and continues to serve the Great Barrington
        community.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_83fb3fd5d3b555a472c26ed008f0c25d">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains the original manuscript covenant and confession of faith for the
        Second North Housatonic Parish of Sheffield. Both are written and signed by Samuel
        Hopkins.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <phystech id="aspace_b31b57161b95994f045bc13fcadd7bb8">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <bibliography id="aspace_cfa9812ab2818969fe6ae5754e68f665">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Conn, Howard J. <emph render="italic">The First Congregational Church of Great Barrington
          1743-1943: A History</emph>. Great Barrington: The Anniversary Year Committee, 1943.
        17.11.1 G79.73 FirCC FC 1943c.1</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname identifier="no2016039445" source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Congregational Church (Great Barrington, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n82017881" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Great Barrington (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname rules="rda" source="local">
        <part>Second North Housatonic Parish of Sheffield (Sheffield, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n91055096" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Sheffield (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_6bb1a09e5321d5bc6b2df66b7805eb59" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Covenant and confession of faith</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1743">1743</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_25f578da196cc3a557cb80986192aa26" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_7d5cea5c6586f534c84898392144ccba" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_25f578da196cc3a557cb80986192aa26">21</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_a70b097b1ea7ff263ddd7fc1e3402cc3">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Sheffield/viewer/ChurchCovenant1743/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
