<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/WatertownMAWest-0994.xml"
      >WatertownMAWest-0994</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/WatertownMAWest-0994.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Watertown, Mass. West Precinct Church covenant, 1709.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2019-06-12</date>
        <num>RG0994</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language>English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS2 - 2013</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard, Second Edition</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2019-06-12T17:55:56+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.5.0</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Wednesday June 12,
          2019 at 17:55</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Watertown, Mass. West Precinct Church covenant, 1709.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG0994</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>1</quantity>
        <unittype>Folder</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <datesingle standarddate="1709">1709</datesingle>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <abstract id="aspace_cebe0ecd1d2893f7a51619f3dd887c79">In 1696 the residents of the town of
        Watertown, Massachusetts, voted to support two meeting houses; the West Precinct Church, was
        established in 1696 to serve the western section of the town. The first meeting house, a
        repurposed building from Newton, was assembled in 1722. In 1738 the town of Waltham was
        incorporated from the West Precinct of Watertown and the church was renamed to the First
        Parish in Waltham. In 1838 the First Parish merged with the Second Religious Society. In
        1958 the First Parish merged with the First Unitarian Church to form the First Parish Church
        in Waltham, Universalist-Unitarian. This collection contains a manuscript copy of the 1709
        version of the covenant of the West Precinct Church.</abstract>
      <origination label="creator">
        <corpname rules="rda" source="local">
          <part>West Precinct Church (Watertown, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_8423ae03bce00b4c39a8dc32dbf4697f">
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_63f43ccc1210e003ce5a5e173721e7d9">
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_8bb0d3284a56cb09195c7114521ec59d">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Watertown, Mass. West Precinct Church covenant, 1709,
        RG0994. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_5129efeeef715278d13daaa2031db251">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>No acquisition information is available for this collection.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <accruals id="aspace_11cadd28739b07e34fa59d6124064035">
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo id="aspace_436cabefe3b51388202d0ae4ac42cef7">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Zachary Bodnar, June 2019, using DACS Second Edition.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_5b26bc35872c18ad43ba857117fcaf4e">
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>In 1696 the residents of the town of Watertown, Massachusetts, voted to support two meeting
        houses. The First Church, which was established in 1630, became the church in the East
        Precinct. A new church, the West Precinct Church, was established in 1696 to serve the
        western section of the town, which was largely a farming community. The first physical
        structure to hold the parish was built in 1696. By 1722 the first church building had become
        unsuitable for the congregation; that year a disused building from Newton was purchased,
        disassembled, and reassembled in Waltham to become the first meeting house. In 1738 the town
        of Waltham was incorporated from the West Precinct of Watertown and the West Precinct Church
        became the First Parish in Waltham. By 1767 the congregation had once again outgrown the
        meeting house and before the end of 1768 the second meeting house was constructed and in
        use.</p>
      <p>By 1813 the First Parish in Waltham was either fully Unitarian or heavily moving towards
        Unitarianism. The Second Religious Society in Waltham formed in 1813, likely in response to
        the ecclesiastical direction of the First Parish. In 1820 this society split again with one
        half forming the First Congregational Church, also known as the Third Trinitarian Society,
        and the other half retained the name, Second Religious Society, but adopted Unitarianism. In
        1838 the Second Congregational Society merged with the First Parish to become the only
        Unitarian congregation in Waltham. At that time the newly merged congregation built the
        third meeting house.</p>
      <p>In 1933 the third meeting house was destroyed by a fire. The fourth meeting house, designed
        by Allen &amp; Collens from Boston, was built on the foundation of the third meeting house.
        The fourth meeting house, a Classic Revival structure, was listed on the National Register
        of Historic Places in 1989. In 1958 the First Parish merged with the First Universalist
        Society of Waltham to become the First Parish Church in Waltham, Universalist-Unitarian.
        This church continues to serve the local community today.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_317f634c723655e91d2c20dfb4aaf523">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains a manuscript copy of the 1709 version of the covenant of the West
        Precinct Church in Watertown, Massachusetts.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <phystech id="aspace_f99119396759b0eab54b2cbcb3bf3cb6">
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <bibliography id="aspace_cf2c7f03170d88cf6a57d723753f35fe">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>"History." First Parish in Waltham. Accessed June 12, 2019. <ref actuate="onrequest"
          href="http://www.walthamuu.org/history" linktitle="History" show="new"
          >http://www.walthamuu.org/history</ref>.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject identifier="sh85025741" source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject identifier="sh85033612" source="lcsh">
        <part>Covenants (Church polity).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <corpname source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Parish in Waltham (Waltham, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n80025792" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Waltham (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
      <corpname identifier="n80037693" source="lcnaf">
        <part>Watertown (Mass.) -- Church history.</part>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_a84b1a693c2b2ae6cbb937b466fb0f50" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Covenant</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <datesingle standarddate="1709">1709</datesingle>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <container id="aspace_a2d2ca946f585a3d1a08c5a8d87f2ad6" label="Mixed Materials"
            localtype="box">NEHH-Small 1</container>
          <container id="aspace_9d454551d450242e565bd60a45f60e5c" localtype="folder"
            parent="aspace_a2d2ca946f585a3d1a08c5a8d87f2ad6">15</container>
        </did>
        <altformavail id="aspace_91970e791befe503c486f3bd6f3b82c4">
          <head>Digital Copies</head>
          <p>These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
            project. Digital reproductions are <ref actuate="onrequest"
              href="http://nehh-viewer.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/#/content/Watertown/viewer/Covenant/1"
              linktitle="available to view online" show="new">available to view online</ref>.</p>
        </altformavail>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
