<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SAA-SDT/EAD3/master/ead3.rng"
      type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="http://ead3.archivists.org/schema/">
  <control countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b"
    relatedencoding="marc" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <recordid
      instanceurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CongregationalLibrary/Finding-Aid-Repository/master/EAD/YarmouthMAFirst.xml"
      >YarmouthMAFirst-5403</recordid>
    <representation localtype="pdf"
      href="https://www.congregationallibrary.org/sites/all/files/YarmouthMAFirst-5403.pdf"/>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Yarmouth, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1729-1888.</titleproper>
        <author>Zachary Bodnar</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>14 Beacon Street</addressline>
          <addressline>Suite 200</addressline>
          <addressline>Boston, MA 02108</addressline>
          <addressline localtype="email">info@14beacon.org</addressline>
          <addressline><ref href="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org"
              linktitle="http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org" show="new"
              >http://www.CongregationalLibrary.org</ref></addressline>
        </address>
        <date>2021-11-17</date>
        <num>RG5403</num>
      </publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>
        <p>This collection is part of New England's Hidden Histories. Digital historical
          representations of the collection can be viewed online.</p>
      </seriesstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <maintenancestatus value="derived"/>
    <maintenanceagency countrycode="US">
      <agencycode>US-MBC</agencycode>
      <agencyname>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</agencyname>
    </maintenanceagency>
    <languagedeclaration>
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languagedeclaration>
    <conventiondeclaration>
      <abbr>DACS 2019.0.3</abbr>
      <citation>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</citation>
    </conventiondeclaration>
    <localcontrol localtype="findaidstatus">
      <term>completed</term>
    </localcontrol>
    <maintenancehistory>
      <maintenanceevent>
        <eventtype value="derived"/>
        <eventdatetime>2022-06-29T14:07:21+00:00</eventdatetime>
        <agenttype value="machine"/>
        <agent>ArchivesSpace v2.8.1</agent>
        <eventdescription>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on Wednesday June 29,
          2022 at 14:07</eventdescription>
      </maintenanceevent>
    </maintenancehistory>
  </control>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Yarmouth, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1729-1888.</unittitle>
      <unitid>RG5403</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>
          <part>Congregational Library &amp; Archives</part>
        </corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial>
        <languageset>
          <language langcode="eng">English</language>
          <script scriptcode="Latn">Latin</script>
        </languageset>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdescstructured coverage="whole" physdescstructuredtype="spaceoccupied">
        <quantity>0.44</quantity>
        <unittype>Cubic Feet</unittype>
      </physdescstructured>
      <physdesc localtype="container_summary">(1 box)</physdesc>
      <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
        <daterange>
          <fromdate standarddate="1729">1729</fromdate>
          <todate standarddate="1888">1888</todate>
        </daterange>
      </unitdatestructured>
      <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
        >1729-1888</unitdate>
      <abstract>The First Congregational Church in Yarmouth, Massachusetts, was likely established
        in 1639. The first minister of the church was Marmaduke Matthews and the first meeting house
        was located in what is today known as Ancient Cemetery. In 1716, the second meeting house
        was constructed close to the location of the first. The third meeting house was constructed
        in 1830 and the fourth, and present, edifice was constructed in 1870. Members were dismissed
        from the First Congregational Church in 1727 and 1840 to form the East Second Church of
        Yarmouth and the South Congregational Church respectively. This collection contains both
        vital records and administrative records. The records include church meeting minutes,
        financial records, ordination and installation records, membership records, baptismal
        records, marriage records, and records of deaths.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <corpname source="lcnaf">
          <part>First Congregational Church (Yarmouth, Mass.)</part>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict>
      <head>Restrictions on Access</head>
      <p>Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict>
      <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
      <p>Items in this collection are subject to U.S. Copyright Law. It is the responsibility of the
        researcher to determine the copyright status of collection items and to secure any
        permissions necessary for their reproduction and publication. Requests for permission to
        publish material must be discussed with the archivist or librarian.</p>
      <p>Digital Reproductions are protected by copyright and/or related rights. You are free to use
        the Digital Reproductions in any way that is permitted by the copyright and related rights
        legislation that applies to your use. In addition, no permission is required from the
        Congregational Library &amp; Archives for educational uses. For other uses, you need to
        obtain permission from the Congregational Library &amp; Archives. For additional information
        regarding copyright, please consult the Congregational Library &amp; Archives' <ref
          actuate="onrequest" href="http://www.congregationallibrary.org/about/digital-copyright"
          linktitle="Digital Collections Copyright &amp; Use" show="new">Digital Collections
          Copyright &amp; Use</ref> policy.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite>
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[Identification of item], in the Yarmouth, Mass. First Congregational Church records,
        1729-1888, RG5403. The Congregational Library &amp; Archives, Boston, MA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo>
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Materials were temporarily deposited for digitization to the Congregational Library &amp;
        Archives by the First Congregational Church of Yarmouth in June 2019; 2019-15.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <originalsloc>
      <head>Location of Originals</head>
      <p>Materials in this collection are held and maintained by the First Congregational Church in
        Yarmouth, Massachusetts.</p>
    </originalsloc>
    <altformavail>
      <head>Digital Copies</head>
      <p>Records within this collection were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories
        project. Digital reproductions may be accessed online through our <ref
          href="https://congregationallibrary.quartexcollections.com/manuscript-collections/browse-the-first-congregational-church-records-in-yarmouth-massachusetts"
          linktitle="view digitial reproductions online" show="new">digital archive</ref>.</p>
    </altformavail>
    <accruals>
      <head>Accruals</head>
      <p>Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text
        transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.</p>
    </accruals>
    <processinfo>
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Zachary Bodnar, November 2021, according to DACS 2019.0.3.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Note</head>
      <p>Due to a fire in 1674 no definite records exist that date back to the founding of the First
        Congregational Church in Yarmouth, Massachusetts. However, the accepted date for the
        establishment of the First Congregational Church is 1639, shortly after the settlement of
        the town. The first minister of the church was Marmaduke Matthews, originally of Swansea
        Wales. The original meeting house was located in what is currently called Ancient
        Cemetery.</p>
      <p>During the pastorate of Daniel Greenleaf, in 1716, the second meeting house was constructed
        close to the location of the first. 33 members of the First Congregational Church were
        dismissed in 1727 so that they could form a church in the newly formed east precinct of
        Yarmouth. The East Second Church of Yarmouth later became the First North Trinitarian Church
        in Dennis and is now the Dennis Union Church. In 1766, during the pastorate of Joseph Green
        Jr., the second meeting house was enlarged in order to accommodate the growing congregation.
        During Timothy Alden's pastorate, the First Congregational Church started its first Sabbath
        school.</p>
      <p>By 1830, the congregation had outgrown its meeting house again and so a new edifice was
        erected that year in Yarmouth Port. In 1840, 64 members were dismissed so that they might
        form another Congregational Church in West Yarmouth. Originally called the South
        Congregational Church, the church is now called the West Yarmouth Congregational Church.</p>
      <p>In the summer of 1870 the first cornerstone was laid for the fourth meeting house of the
        First Congregational Church in Yarmouth. This building was dedicated on November 29, 1870.
        The First Congregational Church continues to worship in the fourth meeting house and
        continues to serve the local community to this day.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection contains both administrative and vital records for the First Congregational
        Church of Yarmouth, Massachusetts in the form of both church and parish record books. The
        administrative records cover topics such as pews and pew deeds, church finances, records
        related to ordinations and installations, meeting minutes, council results, and committee
        records. The vital records contain membership records for admissions and dismissions,
        baptismal records, marriage records, and records of deaths.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection has been arranged in chronological order by start date.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <phystech>
      <head>Technical Requirements</head>
      <p>To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is
        required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari
        5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.</p>
    </phystech>
    <bibliography>
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p><emph render="italic">Manual of the First Congregational Church, Yarmouth, Mass.</emph>
        Yarmouth Port: Register Steam Job Printing Establishment, 1873.</p>
      <p>"Our History." The First Congregational Church of Yarmouth. Accessed November 17, 2021,
          <ref href="https://www.fccyarmouth.org/history"
          linktitle="https://www.fccyarmouth.org/history" show="new"
          >https://www.fccyarmouth.org/history</ref>.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Baptismal records.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Church finance.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Church membership.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Church records and registers.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Installation (clergy).</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Necrologies.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="local">
        <part>New England's Hidden Histories.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Ordination.</part>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">
        <part>Pews and pew rights.</part>
      </subject>
      <persname source="lcnaf">
        <part>Alden, Timothy, 1736-1828</part>
      </persname>
      <persname rules="rda" source="local">
        <part>Cogswell, Nathaniel, 1796-1874</part>
      </persname>
      <corpname source="lcnaf">
        <part>First Congregational Church (Yarmouth, Mass.)</part>
      </corpname>
      <persname rules="rda" source="local">
        <part>Packard, Abel K. (Abel Kingman), 1823-1903</part>
      </persname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1729">1729</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1861">1861</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >1729-1861</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume is a register which contains lists of baptisms, admissions, dismissions,
            and membership lists. The volume also contains the minutes of church meetings, the
            minutes of minutes related to ministerial calls and the choice of deacons, and a copy of
            the result of an ecclesiastical council meeting called for the dismission of Nathaniel
            Cogswell.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c>
      <c level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Parish records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1805">1805</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1888">1888</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >1805-1888</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume of parish records contains financial records and records related to parish
            business. The records include clerk reports, collectors reports, ministerial calls,
            records related to the discussion of a new church building, and general financial
            records. The volume also contains records of pews and pew deeds and an interesting
            record verifying the church's affiliation as something other than Congregational for tax
            purposes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c>
      <c level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Church records</unittitle>
          <unitdatestructured calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive">
            <daterange>
              <fromdate standarddate="1822">1822</fromdate>
              <todate standarddate="1850">1850</todate>
            </daterange>
          </unitdatestructured>
          <unitdate calendar="gregorian" datechar="creation" unitdatetype="inclusive"
            >1822-1850</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <head>Scope and Contents</head>
          <p>This volume of church records, which covers the entirety of Nathaniel Cogswell's
            pastorate, contains records relating to the ordination of Nathaniel Cogswell, admission
            records, dismission records, baptismal records, marriage records, and records of
            deaths.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
